<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The safety of France to Monsieur the Dauphin. Or the secret history of the French king Proving to his son that there is no other way to secure France from approaching ruin, but by desposing his father for a tyrant and destroyer of his people. Done into English from the second edition of the French original printed in Holland. Licens'd and entred according to order.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59404</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830574</idno>
  <idno type="VID">35027</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240879088</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S282D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219038</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830574</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99830574e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59404)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35027)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2111:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The safety of France to Monsieur the Dauphin. Or the secret history of the French king Proving to his son that there is no other way to secure France from approaching ruin, but by desposing his father for a tyrant and destroyer of his people. Done into English from the second edition of the French original printed in Holland. Licens'd and entred according to order.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 154 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Salusbury at the sign of the Temple near Temple Bar in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Louis, --  Dauphin of France, 1661-1711.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  1689-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35027:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35027:1"/>
            <head>THE SAFETY of FRANCE TO Monsieur the <hi>Dauphin.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="discourse">
               <head>The first Discourse.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU must of necessity be a very great Stoick, if you are not very much alarum'd. All the World is Calculating your Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and they boldly affirm that you shall never be a King; and that this next Campaign you shall see most ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Preludes of the Misfortunes which are to befal ye.</p>
               <p>I must acknowledge it is a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult thing to penetrate into Futurity. Nor have all those who have made it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35027:2"/> their business to prophesie in this Age, had the satisfaction to see their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesies accomplish'd. But there are many Things which men may foretel without being Prophets; and the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Diminution of your Glory is an Event so visible, as that it may be easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foreseen, without Revelation, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulting the Stars.</p>
               <p>Considering the present Condition of Affairs, <hi>France</hi> must of necessity sink, if her Enemies act by joynt consent, and that they continue to take the same Measures which they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taken since the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ascended the Throne of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Never flatter your self, Sir, for how Potent soever <hi>France</hi> may be, she can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but see both the Backstroke and Forestroke that threatens her, if she does not betake herself to some spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and extraordinary Remedy. All <hi>Europe</hi> is up in Arms against her, and her Enemies are so much the more Formidable, because they only fight to be reveng'd upon her for the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of bloody Outrages which she has done them, with all manner of Injustice, and to break those Chains
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35027:2"/> and Fetters which she would put about their Necks.</p>
               <p>I need not here make use of any great force of Rhetorick to convince you, that <hi>France</hi> is now no more the same that formerly she was. You see it with your own Eyes. Her Trade, which is as it were the Soul of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is utterly ruin'd, ever since the departure of the Protestants. For that not being able to vent her Native Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities into Foreign Countries, Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty increases every where. To fill her <hi>Exchequer,</hi> she must have recourse to unusual and violent means, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by compleat the utter Exhausting of the Peoples purses. 'Tis true, her Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are very numerous; but besides that, the Souldiers of which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist, are not all of them experienc'd, as being for the most part new rais'd Men: Besides that, there are infinite Numbers which desert her Service, either because they are expos'd to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard and tedious Duty, or else be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they were listed against their Wills. Certain it is, that they have been so accustom'd, for some years past, to vanquish Enemies that were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35027:3"/> not in a condition to withstand them, that they are now no longer fit for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing else but to make new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, or to be employed in burning of Towns and Cities. You have seen something in the Campaign wherein your self commanded, and at the Sieges of <hi>Mayence</hi> and <hi>Bon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Peace which she concluded not long since with the <hi>Algerines,</hi> is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident sign that she knows not where she is. For you cannot deny, but that if she thought her self strong enough to repel her Enemies, or to make the least Resistance, she would never have purchas'd, upon such ignominious Conditions, an Alliance with a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous People, who are the Scorn of all the Earth, and from whom she has receiv'd those Affronts that she ought never to have pardon'd.</p>
               <p>In a word, Sir, for you may delude your self, with all her Forces both by Sea and Land, with all her Alliances with the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> and the <hi>Alge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines,</hi> with all her Preparations and her Threatnings, is at this day only upon the Defensive part; she that formerly so vigorously assail'd others. And you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35027:3"/> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but acknowledge, that since the Siege of <hi>Philipsbourgh,</hi> where you sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliz'd your self in a manner so distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished from the rest, has all along gone down the Hill, which is no good Omen.</p>
               <p>What would you have me say to yee, considering the condition of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs? I must, in spite of my Teeth, foretel you dismal Things; and if you will but reflect upon them you will tell your self the same. You cannot be ignorant of the danger to which an imprudent Policy has expos'd so great a Kingdom, which gave Laws to all <hi>Europe;</hi> and in the mean time you will do well to rid your self of those trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous and mercinary Souls which put it into your Head, that <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> is the greatest Prince that ever was, and that he shall triumph, with ease, over the most powerful and strongest League that ever was form'd against a Monarch.</p>
               <p>If you were a Prince but of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Merit, or that you could not see with your own Eyes, we might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our selves with lamenting your Misfortunes, when we came to cast
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35027:4"/> an Eye upon your future Destiny. But considering the surmounting Parts and Qualities which you have receiv'd from Heaven, you will be unpitied by all People, if the Arms of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates should subdue the Monarchy of <hi>France,</hi> and reduce you, after their Conquest, to a private Life. For you must agree to this, that you your self were accessary to your own Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
               <p>Therefore, Sir, open your Eyes at once: <hi>France</hi> is upon the brink of a Precipice, from whence she will never be able to save herself, if once she hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to fall. Suffer not your Mind to be inchanted, nor listen to your Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers. The Condition of <hi>France</hi> is a thousand times more deplorable than can be expressed by all the Aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we can make use of. Nevertheless, her Distemper is not altogether incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; you may apply a remedy to it still. However, Sir, deceive not your self; for desperate Diseases, must have despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Cures.</p>
               <p>I confess it were to be wish'd that the King would make a Peace with all the Princes that are engaged in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35027:4"/> Arms against him, could he but make them satisfaction for all the Ravage and Spoil which he has committed in their Countries: but this is a way not to be put in practise. For besides that, there is not any State that will be willing to treat with a Prince, who believes that Policy permits him never to keep his Word, and who, contrary to the Faith of Treaties, has committed unheard of Hostilities in the Territories of all his Neighbours; What likelyhood is there that a King, who aspired to Universal Monarchy, who has extended his Conquests every way, and who never condescended to a Peace, but what was advantageous to him, will renounce all at once such great pretensions, and restore back all that he has so usurp'd?</p>
               <p>Certainly the King can never take such a course, as would absolutely tarnish all his Glory, and render him the most contemptible of all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the World. For, Sir, he must not think to flatter himself in this matter; the Confederates will never yield to an Accommodation, unless they make the Conditions themselves; and you well know, that the Law
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35027:5"/> which the strongest side prescribes, is always that which must be obeyed. He must restore to the Emperor, and the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> all that he has conquered from them, ever since he ascended his Throne; and he must also sacrifice to his Imperial Majesty the <hi>Cardinal</hi> of <hi>Furstembergh,</hi> to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht after a most exemplary manner, for all his Treasons and perfidious Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. He must make the same Resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions to the Most <hi>Catholic King,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> He must demolish the Forts and Cittadels which he has built upon the Frontiers of the <hi>Switzers.</hi> He must restore <hi>Pignerol,</hi> and <hi>Casal.</hi> He must restore to his <hi>Holiness</hi> the Franchises, Regal Right, and other Priviledges of that nature, which he disputed so haughtily and violently with his Predecessor, <hi>Innocent</hi> the XI. He must humble himself before <hi>Prince Joseph Clement</hi> of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> He must make Satisfaction to the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces for an infinite number of Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels which he has seiz'd within his Ports, in time of Peace, and which his Privateers have taken. He must
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35027:5"/> reimburse the <hi>Genoeses</hi> immense Sums of Money, which they have been, and are still obliged to expend in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building the sumptuous Palace which he thunder'd down, when he threw his Bombs into their Magnificent City. And You yourself must go in Person, and throw your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self at the Feet of their Duke, to make him Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for the<note n="*" place="margin">A most ignominious Punishment inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an extream Offender, who must go through the Streets barefoot and bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, with a burning Link in his Hand, to the Seat of Justice, and there confess his Offences, and ask Forgiveness of the Party wrong'd.</note>
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men de Honarable,</hi> which he was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to undergo, after your Father had treated the <hi>Genoeses</hi> like so many Barbarians, and that upon a vain and ridiculous pretence. It would become him also to make an Alliance with the King of <hi>England, William</hi> III. whom he looks upon as an Usurper, and whom he has treated hitherto with a more than ordinary contempt. And in regard, that because there is a great Vacuity in his Exchequer, which is more and more exhausted every day, that he would not be rich enough to rebuild so many Cities, Towns, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35027:6"/> Castles, which he has burnt in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> more especially in the Territories of the <hi>Elector Palatine,</hi> it would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, that to appease the Princes interested, he should burn his own Capital City; or at least his Castles of <hi>Versailles</hi> and <hi>St. Germain.</hi> It would behove him to recal the Protestants whom he has constrained to quit their Estates and their Country, by exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing upon them the most unjust and most unheard of Persecutions; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build all their Churches, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Edicts of the Pacification granted by <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth: For why should the Protestants be left out, if he makes a General Peace. And that I may not enter into a longer Display of his Pranks, it would behove him sor the Security as well of those without, as those within, to send into <hi>Holland,</hi> or into <hi>England,</hi> Monsieur the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> or some other of his Children; for we would willingly call back those Ages, wherein they never made any Treaty, but the Prince to whom the Peace was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, gave not only Hostages, but Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stages of his own Blood.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:35027:6"/>
               <p>Never question it, all these Things must be done; the Confederates will not bate him an Ace: they will every one have a Fleece from his back; and if you seriously consider it, 'tis no more than what you must confess to be but just and reasonable.</p>
               <p>So then, Sir, you must agree with me in this, that the King cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Peace, thô it should be offer'd him; because he will never accept upon mean and prejudicial Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>What will Posterity say of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> if after such an Enlargement of Conquest every way, and if after having been so near being Master of all <hi>Christendom,</hi> he should voluntarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine himself within the Bounds of the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy, rather than conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a War which he first kindled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self? If after his having made <hi>France</hi> all Roman Catholic, and having there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by gain'd an Honour to which his Predecessors in vain aspir'd, he should be forc'd to build Calvinistical Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and set forth Declarations in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Heresie? he would be lookt upon as the most pitiful and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35027:7"/> of Princes. And indeed if he should condescend to sully his glorious and renowned Atchievements by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descension so mean and poor, I must appeal to you, Sir, what Thoughts would you your self have of him?</p>
               <p>Nevertheless, in regard there is no other way, but by the means of a Peace for <hi>France</hi> to divert the threatning Tempest, there is no body but your self that can make it, if you intend to preserve the Honour of <hi>France.</hi> For besides that, the Confederates, who at present breath nothing but fire and slaughter, will deal more mildly and civilly with you, than with a Prince that aspired only to enslave them, and made a War with them after a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner unheard of among Christians. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that, both the one and the other are weary of seeing so much blood shed, and such wasts of their own and their Peoples Treasure, most certain it is, that which way soever Fortune wheels, and how hard soever the Clauses may be, to which you you shall be obliged to subscribe, all the World will admire yee. For in a word, as you have not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed at all to the Misfortunes that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35027:7"/> threaten <hi>France,</hi> and in regard there is not any Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> that is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how much you have bewail'd the villanous Courses and false Measures that have been taken in the Kingdom, they will look upon you as a wise Prince, who has rather chose the sure way, than to hazard a Crown. Sir, you may yield to all things, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store to every one that which belongs to him, without having your Honour any may interested in such a Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scension, in regard it was not you that were guilty of the Usurpations.</p>
               <p>And without any Injury to the Religion which you profess, you may renew the Edicts which give a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to the Protestants, in regard it is a Prerogative inseparable from Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to overturn, so soon as they come to the Throne, whatever their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors have done; it being no more but what all Princes, even Popes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, tho' it be their Interest to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the whole World that St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Successors are no less infallible in all their Actions, than was the Prince of the Apostles.</p>
               <p>I well know, Sir, what Answer you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35027:8"/> will make me. You will say, You are not yet invested with the Royal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and that according to all Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, not being likely long to be so, it is in vain for me to propose a fruitless Expedient, that cannot be put in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
               <p>I confess, Sir, that you are not yet King; and that you are also far from being so. For that, if we may judge according to probabilities, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the great Maladies which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, he may live per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, as long as you; besides that, it will always be the interest of those that are prevalent with him, cunningly to insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, as they do, that your Marriage with a Princess of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> must render you continually suspected; and that you are otherwise unfit for any thing else, but either for a Masquerade, or to hunt the Wolf. Now after these consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, you will never be in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to make that happy Peace which <hi>France</hi> so passionately desires: You will be in danger of dying a Subject, and of being the Son and Father of a King, yet never come to the Crown your self, as some of your false Priests have fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35027:8"/> Then again, they who by their unhappy Counsels have reduced <hi>France</hi> to that deplorable Condition wherein it is at present, are your most cruel E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. For in regard they enrich themselves by the publick Disorders, and very well understand that only you, who have the Helm in your Hand, are able to struggle with the Tempest, they make the King believe you to be a person unfit for the Government, as being a Prince without sense, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slav'd to his pleasures; and if I may venture to say so, a weak and silly Prince, under pretence that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd it to be a great piece of Policy to dissemble hitherto, and act the part of that illustrious <hi>Roman,</hi> who expell'd the <hi>Tarquins</hi> out of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheless, Sir, however it be, the Proposition which I now make you, is no such difficulty not to be surmount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It will be your fault if you are not King in despite of all your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, if you ardently desire it: nor is it necessary for you to stay till the death of a Prince, who, considering his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, is not yet in a condition to dye. You have lain close a sufficient
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35027:9"/> time, it behoves yee now to discover your self, and that appearing in your Natural Colours, you should let <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. see, that you are a Prince who deserves to bear the Name of <hi>Bourbon;</hi> and that it is not to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that you have been educated in so many several sorts of Sciences; and that Policy is not the only Thing of which you are ignorant, tho' you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made it your business, because you would not give Occasion of Suspicion. It behoves yee to set to work that Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which they say is so natural to yee; and that you unhoodwink your Father's Eyes, by laying before him the strength of his Enemies, the weakness of his Armies, the consternation of his People, the fears of Domestick Insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and least the Troops of the Confederates should pour into his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to the end he may agree with you, that there is no other way but by a Peace to shelter himself from the Storm; and therefore since he cannot obtain it himself, but upon Conditions that will be altogether dishonourable to a Prince that has been hitherto esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Greatest of his Age, that it is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35027:9"/> absolutely necessary for him to abdicate the Government for your sake, and that he should go and end his days in Retirement, since he cannot attain his Ends of mounting the Throne of <hi>Charlemaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not, Sir, but that you have your Creatures at Court; not but that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam the <hi>Dauphiness,</hi> who is a Lady of exquisite Abilities, has already made herself Mistress of the Hearts and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of those Ladies which at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Rule the King; and not but that your Father's Favourites and Governors have given you several Testimonies of their being devoted to your Interests: they have been too cunning to omit the performance of those Ceremonies. You must therefore make use of them at this time, and absolutely fix both the one and the other to your Interests, by flattering them with great Hopes and Expectations, as it is easie for you to do, to the end they may act by consent in advancing you to the Throne.</p>
               <p>Believe me, Sir, if you would but speak seriously and boldly to the King, yet observing the Limits of respect and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35027:10"/> duty to a King and Father; and if on the other side, his Favourites, Mistres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and Governors of his Conscience, would but slily and cunningly insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate into his Breast, that he cannot save his Kingdom, support his Reputation and Honour, and gain Paradise, unless he take this only Course, you will stag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger him without question; and rather than hazard the Fate with which the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> threaten <hi>Bajezet,</hi> he will rather choose of his own accord to shut himself up in a Desert, there to do Penance the remainder of his Life, for the Crimes of his Prosperity.</p>
               <p>'Tis a violent choice, I must confess, and I make no question, the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves himself to be in no great haste as yet to lament his sins. But what is that to the purpose, Sir; You know very well, Sir, that of two Evils the least is to be chosen. The Crown which he abandons is not worth the <hi>Risco</hi> which he runs. And since after all, it would be better for him to do it voluntarily, than to be obliged by constraint and force, as it befel <hi>Alphonso</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> who seeing <hi>Charles</hi> the VIII. come thundring down into his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> caus'd his Son
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35027:10"/>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> to be Crown'd, and retired into <hi>Scicily</hi> for Security.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Alphonso,</hi> whose Life was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Famous Historian <hi>Philip Commines,</hi> and so often read by <hi>Charles the Fifth,</hi> had contaminated his Reign with a Thousand Crimes: He had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd an infinite number of Cruelties; he had put to death his nearest Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Relations; he had ravish'd the Wives of his Subjects, and reduced his People to utmost Beggery. But this Resignation of his Crown to his Son, was the means which God made use of for his Conversion: For having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd himself in a kind of Solitude, and there conforming himself to the Rules of the <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> he liv'd as holy a Life as if he had been one of the <hi>Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let not the <hi>King</hi> stay, till an Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of this Nature overtake him, least it should utterly deface the Lustre of all his great Actions. For in regard his Life has been so conformable to that of the King of <hi>Naples,</hi> he may as well follow the Example of his Cowardly Fear, and try to seek some Sanctuary within the Ottoman Empire, so soon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35027:11"/> as he shall see the Imperial <hi>Leopold,</hi> or the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ready to pour in upon him. Let him do that volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily, which <hi>Alphonso</hi> was forc'd to do, and let him leave you a Crown, for which you will have no reason to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with the Enemies of <hi>France,</hi> as the young <hi>Ferdinand</hi> was constrain'd to contend for his with <hi>Charles</hi> the VIII. For perhaps the same Fate may attend you as befel that Prince, whom <hi>Charles</hi> continually pursued till he had totally vanquish'd, and expell'd him out of his Territories.</p>
               <p>Therefore let him never study upon it, but resign the Government into your hands without any more ado, since he cannot do a thing more to his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; more especially since there are so many Presidents to encourage him to an Act so Heroick, and proceeding altogether from accomplish'd Policy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nerva,</hi> who was elected Emperour after the death of <hi>Domitian,</hi> resigned the Empire to <hi>Trajan</hi> so soon as he found himself incapable to govern, by reason of his Infirmities and his Age. You know the History of <hi>Dioclesian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Emperour, who according to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35027:11"/> the Testimony of all those that have wrote his History, was only born for Government and War; that Emperour, of whom it is said, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Arms were ne're in such a flourishing condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as under his Empire; that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, who subdu'd where e're he came, who had vanquish'd several Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and to whom several Trophies had been erected, <hi>for having extended the Roman Empire both to the East and West; and for having rooted out the Name of Christians from the Earth.</hi> This Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour nevertheless, in the midst of his Triumphs and Victories, resigned the Empire to <hi>Galerias;</hi> and the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of that Resignation was publickly perform'd three Miles from the City of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> where after he had rande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz'd his Army together, addressing his Speech to his Souldiers, he told them, <hi>That being become infirm, he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to retire to a Life of Repose, after so many Labours and Travels which he had been constrain'd to undergo; to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he would surrender the Empire into the hands of such Persons as were able to bear the weight of it.</hi> And having so said, he named <hi>Galerius</hi> for his Successor, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35027:12"/> presently invested him with his own Purple Robes: And so resuming his true Name of <hi>Diocles,</hi> which he had chang'd for that of <hi>Dioclesian,</hi> he retir'd like a common Souldier that has receiv'd his discharge from Service, and lead a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Life for several Years. He made choice of <hi>Satorrica</hi> for his Retirement, and found so much pleasure in Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that all Charms of pleasure could never tempt him forth again: at what time he also protested, That he never tasted the True Pleasures of Life, nor saw the Sun shine with so much delight, as since he resign'd the Empire.</p>
               <p>Now would not the King of <hi>France</hi> be happy to end the remainder of his days, as the same Emperour did. Let him rest from his Labours, seeing that considering the Condition to which he has reduced <hi>France,</hi> it is not possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he should reduce any real Repose. Let him like another <hi>Atlas</hi> ease his Shoulders of a Burden which he is no longer able to bear, and set it upon yours. It is high time you should Reign for the general good and safety of the People, seeing that so long as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35027:12"/>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> rules, his Reign must prove fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to the People. Let him imitate <hi>Dioclesian</hi> in this generous Action, who has followed his Example in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lothaire</hi> the I. the Son of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Debonnair,</hi> is another <hi>President</hi> which I cannot pass by in silence: This Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Prince whom nothing would serve, but to dethrone his Father, thô he had made him his Companion in the Empire, being advanced to the Throne, after the death of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, and having undergone an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of Hardships, parted his Territories between his Children, and taking a Religious Habit in the Abby of <hi>Prume,</hi> near <hi>Treves,</hi> dy'd in a short time after.</p>
               <p>But why should I search for Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in Ages so far remote, for to shew that such a Resignation is no Disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to a Prince, we have a Decent Example to produce.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christina Queen</hi> of <hi>Sweden,</hi> succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Gustavus Adolphus</hi> in the Year 1633: This Princess govern'd her Territories very happily; and being descended from the Blood of the Great <hi>Gustavus,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35027:13"/> she was formidable to her Enemies; besides that she was distinguish'd from the rest of her Sex by an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Noble Endowments, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd her the Admiration of the World: Other Kingdoms envied the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of <hi>Sweden:</hi> for in short, a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom cannot chuse but be happy, when govern'd by Princes that are Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, or Philosophers that are Princes, according to the Opinion of one of the Ancients: Nevertheless this Queen, as happy and glorious as she was, resign'd her Crown and Scepter in the Year 1654, to <hi>Charles Gustavus.</hi> The Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of the Court, and all her Subjects were much troubled at her Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and endeavoured to disswade her from it; but all their perswasions were in vain. She summon'd an As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of her Estates, where were present all the Nobility, and all the Forreign Ministers. There the Chief Minister invested her with her Royal Robes, and set the Crown upon her Head. After which, she sate a while upon her Throne with her Scepter in her Right Hand, and the Golden Ball in her Left Hand. All this, for no
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35027:13"/> other purpose, but to be immediately Disrob'd again, and to surrender the Ensigns of her Royal Authority to her Successor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Casimir</hi> the V. who after the death of <hi>Ladislaus,</hi> his Brother, was Elected King of <hi>Poland,</hi> was no less happy, during his Reign, than <hi>Christina</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hers. He was no sooner settl'd in his Throne, but he became the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his Enemies: And to speak all his Actions in a word, this Prince had been a Victor in no less than se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen or eighteen Battels, where he was present in person. Nevertheless, what does <hi>Casimir</hi> do in the midst of all his Triumphs? Over-burthen'd with the weight of his Scepter, and so many Lawrel-Wreaths wherewith he had encircled his Brows; tir'd with the Glorious Travels which had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him the bravest Prince of his Age; weari'd with continual Conquest, and shedding so much Blood; and lastly, looking upon all the Victories which he could expect to win, as not able to repair the loss of his beloved Queen, he voluntarily resign'd his Crown, and ended his days in a Monastery.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35027:14"/>
               <p>Are not these great Examples, Sir, sufficient to move ye? And if you were in <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth's Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, would you make any difficulty to follow them? A <hi>Heroess,</hi> of an exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Descent, whom <hi>France</hi> admired, and treated like a Queen, after she had renounc'd her Royal Authority, and whom the Popes themselves e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed as the <hi>Palladium</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> A <hi>Hero,</hi> that sacrificed all his worldly Pomp, to lead a Religious Life, and whom the King himself honour'd with one of the most wealthy and famousest Abbies of his Kingdom. In a word, a Queen and a King whose Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was the greatest Elogies that was given them by all that made their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyricks. This incomparable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, and this Prince most worthy to be Sainted, think ye, they will not mollifie the King's Heart, when he reflects upon the many Misfortunes that threaten both His and Your Head, if he continues to Reign Six Months longer. Let him then cease to be a King, if he intends to die a King, and avert from <hi>France</hi> the most terrible <hi>Catastrophe</hi> that ever befel her since the Reign of <hi>Pharamund.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:35027:14"/>
               <p>They may tell us, till Dooms-day, that it was the love of Liberty which inclin'd Q. <hi>Christina</hi> to that surprizing Change. And that <hi>Casimir,</hi> as great as he was, being before a Jesuit, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in that Order, a certain Spice of Phanaticism, which is the principle Character of the Disciples of <hi>Loyola,</hi> who was the greatest <hi>Phanatick</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appeared in the World. 'Tis true, I knew a certain<note n="*" place="margin">The Deceased Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was used to say, That he was acquainted with Three Illustrious Fools; the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Vernuel</hi> who had quitted an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of <hi>600000</hi> Elvers a year for a Wife. Monsieur <hi>Turenne,</hi> who had taken the Holy Ghost out of his Heart, to wear him upon his Coat; and K. <hi>Casimir</hi> who had quitted a Crown to turn Monk.</note> Prince, who was accustomed to say, That among the Fools of that Age, one of the greatest was <hi>Casimir.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>Christina</hi> accompted the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest Woman in the world. Every thing is folly, Sir, when they are taken in a wrong sense. But that which, appears to be folly, is many times a great piece of Wisdom, when the thing comes to be examined. <hi>Moses</hi> was lookt upon as a Fool by the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> when he forsook the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Court, and trampled under foot the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35027:15"/> Crown which was design'd him by the Daughter of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> And yet where was ever a wiser man in the World, than that same <hi>Hebrew Legislator?</hi> Who ever read the Heart of Queen <hi>Christina</hi> to know so well her Inclinations? And as for King <hi>Casimir,</hi> tho' he were a <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit,</hi> are all the <hi>Jesuits</hi> Visionaries. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stina,</hi> even to the last gasp, gave au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Marks, that she was in good earnest when she forsook <hi>Lutheranism,</hi> to embrace the Popes Religion; and <hi>Casimir</hi> dyed like a Saint in the obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Discipline and Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Order. Why therefore must Religion be deny'd to have a share in their Changes, or why may it not be thought to be an Effect of triumphing Grace?</p>
               <p>But to set Religion aside; it cannot be denied but that there may be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Human Prudence or Policy at least. For indeed what could a Woman have done, had she been to su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain a terrible War; if those Enemies which <hi>Gustavus</hi> had so often harass'd, had come to awaken her, and had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd to have satisfaction from the Daughter for the Mischiefs and Losses
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35027:15"/> which they had suffered by the Father? Must she not have sank under the Burthen, and run the Venter of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by force which she did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out constraint? And as for <hi>Casimir,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had expelled <hi>Gustavus,</hi> who had made himself Master of a great part of his Territories, after he had obtained that famous Victory from the <hi>Musco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> in the Year 1661. lastly, after he had gained sixteen or eighteen Battels, what could he expect more? There could be no Accumulation of Honour to that great Hero. He had carried on his Affairs as far as a Prince could carry them. He had setled his Throne, and restored Peace to his People. He feared nothing; and so himself the most happy Prince then living. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, all things being subject to vicis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citude, and Fortune being blind, was not <hi>Casimir</hi> very prudent, that he might avoid the running of any dangerous ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, or feeling the smart of any back-blow, generously to resign the Scepter which he so well deserv'd to sway? Thrice happy Princes who are able to make their Reflections upon Actions so Heroick, and accompanied with so
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35027:16"/> much prudence! And thrice happy <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. if seeing himself upon the brink of <hi>Ruin,</hi> he would follow the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Christina</hi> and <hi>Casimir,</hi> thereby to preserve to himself the Title of <hi>Great,</hi> and such a place in History, as might obscure the Lustre of the <hi>Alexanders</hi> and <hi>Caesars.</hi> For do but observe, Sir, tho every thing should not justly foretel to the King an inevitable Declination of his Glory; tho' his Kingdom were in as soft a Peace as <hi>Swedeland</hi> or <hi>Poland,</hi> when <hi>Christina</hi> and <hi>Casimir</hi> resigned; tho' he had all the World at command; tho' he had no Enemies, but were as he was formerly, Arbitrator of Peace and War; does he not know that the most flourishing Kingdoms are subject to the greatest Revolutions; that there are certain Bounds, at which it behoves a Prince to stop; that the most settled Prosperities are liable to the severest Crosses; that it is the Glory of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch that has been happy for a long time, not to dye miserable; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he ought to take all the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imaginable to keep the Balance of Fortune even, especially when the Scale ceases to incline most of his side.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:35027:16"/>
               <p>That <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Lydia,</hi> who had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himself so famous by his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests and his Wealth, was at length vanquish'd by <hi>Cyrus;</hi> and of the most fortunate of Princes, in a moment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the most miserable and unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of Mortals. Had not <hi>Croesus</hi> been dazled with the false Lustre of his <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur,</hi> he would have been so far from laughing at <hi>Solon,</hi> who told him that a Prince was not to boast of his Prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, till it was impossible for him to be unhappy, that he would have hid himself in the middle of some Desert, to have avoided the Ignominy of being a Slave to the King of <hi>Persia,</hi> after all the World had done him Homage. Who knows but that <hi>Christina</hi> and <hi>Casi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir</hi> had some wise <hi>Solon,</hi> to whom they listned more attentively, then <hi>Croesus</hi> did to the wise man of <hi>Greece?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let us say no more of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> or the Queen of <hi>Sweden.</hi> The one was a Phanatick, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lov'd a licentious Liberty. We grant that they were not guided either by Religion or Policy. But what say you, Sir, or rather what can your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther object against the Example of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35027:17"/>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the V. That great Prince, as you well know, was neither <hi>Libertine,</hi> nor <hi>Visionary;</hi> nevertheless he resigned the <hi>Empire,</hi> and confin'd himself in <hi>Spain</hi> to the Monastery of St. <hi>Justus,</hi> of the Order of St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> where he end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his days two or three years after he had liv'd like a simple Monk, he who formerly could hardly content himself with several Kingdoms which he pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed in three parts of the World.</p>
               <p>Certainly this is such an Example as must convince his Majesty of the great necessity that there is for him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign his Government, if he loves the Safety of his People, and be but any thing jealous of his own Glory; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially having much more reason than that Emperour. For not to dissemble with you in any thing, <hi>Charles</hi> the V. was a greater Prince than ever <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. He was more prosperous than he, tho' he had not always success: he was more Potent and more formidable; and at the time when he first bethought himself of retiring, beside that he was at peace in <hi>Germany</hi> ever after the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Passau,</hi> he was also at the Head of Fourscore or a Hundred thousand
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35027:17"/> men, being at War with only one Prince, whom he had reason to fear, by reason of the Match which he had made between <hi>Philip</hi> his Son, and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Daughter and Heiress of <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless, in the midst of this Calm, and when he had the least rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to fear any cross stroke of Fortune, at a time when every thing prospered with him, and that his Armies were triumphant, he stops in the midst of his Career, and prudently politick, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, if not real Misfortunes, yet such as were possible to happen: For who can fetter Fortune so, that she shall not be able to break her Chains?</p>
               <p>The Fate of so many Victors, whose <hi>Exits</hi> had prov'd so dismal; the great hopes which he had of those, of whom he had made choice for the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Empire; and the Desire he had to save his Soul, by a total Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of the World, made him determine of a suddain to resign the Imperial Soveraignty, and one of the highest Degrees that a Prince could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at in this World.</p>
               <p>To this end he sent for <hi>Philip</hi> his Son
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35027:18"/> King of <hi>England,</hi> to whom, in favour of his Marriage, he had bequeathed the Kingdoms of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Scicily,</hi> with the Dutchy of <hi>Milan,</hi> and having as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled together the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Low Countries</hi> at <hi>Brussels,</hi> he presently crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Philip</hi> Soveraign of the Order of the <hi>Golden Fleece,</hi> and gave him the Dominion of those Provinces. A month after this Resignation, in pursuance of which, the <hi>States</hi> did Homage to their new Lord, and swore Fealty and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to him; the Deputies of the rest of his Territories being met at the same place, he compleated the general Resignation of all his other Territories and Signiories, as well in <hi>Europe</hi> as in the <hi>New World,</hi> and invested <hi>Philip</hi> in them, reserving no more for his own support, than Two hundred thousand <hi>Ducats</hi> a year, with some Houshold Furniture.</p>
               <p>'Tis true that he did not at first re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign the Empire to his Brother <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand;</hi> but he had an extraordinary reason for that: For he was willing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he abdicated the Empire, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige <hi>Ferdinand</hi> that <hi>Philip</hi> should be ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted King of the <hi>Romans.</hi> But when he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35027:18"/> saw that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> was resolv'd to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that Crown for his own Son, and that for a whole year together his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations had prov'd fruitless, he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined before he left <hi>Brussels,</hi> to perfect his Design. So that after he had caused his Resignation to be drawn up in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Form, he entrusted it in the Hands of <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Nassau,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange, Gregory Sigismund Hold,</hi> Vice-Chancellour of the Empire, and <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> his Secretary, who under the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Ambassadors, carried it to the first Diet that was assembled, made it known to the Electors, and delivered it into the hands of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> together with the Scepter and Crown, and other Ensigns of the Imperial Dignity.</p>
               <p>I shall not say any thing of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Honours that were paid to <hi>Charles</hi> the V. after he had despoil'd himself of all his Dignities, tho' it make for my purpose. For in short, it proves that such Renunciations are no ways ignominious, as the King perhaps may be induced to believe. I shall only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, that when <hi>Charles</hi> departed from <hi>Brussels</hi> for <hi>Gaunt,</hi> in order to his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage into <hi>Spain,</hi> where he had chos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:35027:19"/> his Retirement, he was accompanied by the Duke and Dutchess of <hi>Savoy,</hi> by the Dukes of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Parma,</hi> and a vast number of other great Lords; and which is more, there were in that magnificent Train, no less than five crown'd Heads; <hi>Philip</hi> his Son, King of <hi>Spain, England,</hi> and <hi>Naples; Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia; Ferdinand</hi>'s Son in Law; the King of <hi>Tunis; Elianor</hi> Queen Dowager of <hi>France;</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> Queen Dowager of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> who were both Sisters.</p>
               <p>This Funeral Attendance, if I may so call it, upon a Prince that was dying to the World, is a proof not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul'd, that his Act and Deed was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and lookt upon as Heroick. For you must agree with me in this, Sir, that he had never been treated af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter so magnificent a manner, if that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signation had been any stain to his Life, or any blot to his Reputation in Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Conclude then, Sir, with me, That <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. ought to follow the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Great <hi>Charles</hi> the First, by resigning his Soveraignty to you, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the same Reasons which obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35027:19"/> that Emperour to resign his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and Kingdoms to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> his Brother, and <hi>Philip</hi> the II. his Son, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige also your Father, besides an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of other Motives no less considerable. For indeed Sir, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the great Elogies that are eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day given to the King, yet certain it is, that he is much inferiour to <hi>Charles</hi> the First. So that if <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. resemble that Emperour in any thing, it is in his aspiring like him to the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversal Monarchy, in his excessive Persecution of the Protestants; in his embroiling himself and quarrelling with the <hi>Holy See;</hi> in raising himself an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of Enemies; and in not believing that it was the true Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Prince to be a slave to his Word. Tho' we have more to say of the Emperour, that he did sometimes scruple to falsifie his Word, as in the Case of <hi>Luther,</hi> when he appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him at the <hi>Diet</hi> of <hi>Worms</hi> in the year 1521. At what time his Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Clergy-men advised him to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Example of the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,</hi> not to keep his Word with that <hi>Arch-Heretick,</hi> upon the Faith of which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35027:20"/> he had appear'd at the Diet; but <hi>Charles</hi> would by no means listen to them, and then it was that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced that Golden Saying, which ought to be in the Mouths of all Princes: <hi>That if Faith of Promise were to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd out of the World, the Palaces of Princes ought to give it Sanctuary:</hi> But, Sir, setting aside what I have instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, there is no Comparison between these two Princes; at least you will agree with me, that <hi>Charles</hi> the V. was the most happy and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth was Elected Emperor after the death of <hi>Maximilian</hi> his Grandfather, he had for his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor <hi>Francis</hi> I. King of <hi>France,</hi> who having long design'd to add the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown to his own, had to that purpose form'd several Intreigues in <hi>Germany,</hi> while <hi>Maximilian</hi> was alive, and after his death, which was the reason of an <hi>Interregnum.</hi> In the mean while, seeing that <hi>Charles</hi> the V. got the better of <hi>Francis</hi> the I. because he had the advantage of labouring more diligently under-hand in the <hi>Electoral Colledge,</hi> than his Competitor, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35027:20"/> that the Emperor was born in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and <hi>Francis</hi> was a Forreigner, which chiefly swayed with the Electors not to give him their Suffrages. This begat a Quarrel: and the War con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd between these two potent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, till at length, it being the Fate of <hi>Francis</hi> to be always unfortunate when he had to do with <hi>Charles</hi> the V. he was taken Prisoner at the Battel of <hi>Pavia,</hi> in the Year 1525, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leas'd, but upon Conditions very dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageous to <hi>France,</hi> as you may very well imagine. The King never took any Soveraign Prince Prisoner; and you must allow, that thô <hi>Charles</hi> the V. had never had but that single Honour in his Life, he would have been always lookt upon as much more fortunate than <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all his Conquests since his Advancement to the Throne. To which we may add, That thô <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. in the several Wars which he has made, had taken any King Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner, he could not have thereby gain'd any great Honour; for that all the World knows, that the Princes, with whom he has hitherto had any thing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35027:21"/> to do, excepting <hi>William</hi> the III. are not to be compared with <hi>Francis</hi> the I. who without all contradiction, was the most couragious Prince of his Age.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Francis</hi> the I. was not the only Prince that fell into the hands of <hi>Charles</hi> the V. For <hi>Clement</hi> the VII. some time after, had the same Fate. That Pope had made a League with <hi>France,</hi> the Republics of <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Florence,</hi> and the Cantons of <hi>Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to expel the <hi>Spaniards</hi> out of <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> who at that time besieged Duke <hi>Sforza,</hi> in the Castle of <hi>Milan.</hi> And <hi>Charles</hi> the V. as good a Catholick as he was, to be reveng'd of his Holiness, having sent an Army into <hi>Italy,</hi> under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> besieged <hi>Rome,</hi> took it, and sackt it, and constrain'd the <hi>Pope</hi> to shut himself up in the Castle of St. <hi>Angelo,</hi> with all his Cardinals; and after he had paid for his Ransome about Forty or Fifty thousand Crowns in Gold, was glad to make a Peace with the Emperor, in the Year 1529, by the Marriage of <hi>Alexander de Medici,</hi> his Nephew, with <hi>Margaret,</hi> the natural
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35027:21"/> Daughter of <hi>Charles.</hi> You must ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, Sir, that the King had never these Advantages over any Pope, thô he has had many Quarrels with the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Enterprize of <hi>Gigeri,</hi> in the Year 1664, and his Bombing of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers,</hi> were nothing in comparison with what <hi>Charles</hi> the V. did, the same Year that he came to an Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation with the Pope. He drove <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyman</hi> the <hi>Magnificent</hi> from before <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and some Years after crossed over into <hi>Africa,</hi> with an Army of above fifty thousand Men, took the strong Fort of <hi>Gouletta,</hi> and restored <hi>Muley Hassen</hi> to his Kingdom of <hi>Tunis.</hi> Whereas the Enterprize of <hi>Gigeri</hi> prov'd unfortunate and disgraceful to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. and by his <hi>Bombing</hi> of <hi>Argiers,</hi> he did no more then only a little incommode the Barbarians, who never much trouble themselves for the loss of their sorry Houses; and were so far from submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themselves, that they grew more insolent in their Affronts to <hi>France,</hi> than they were before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lastly,</hi> Sir, That Emperour took Prisoners <hi>John Frederick,</hi> Elector of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35027:22"/>
                  <hi>Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> Landgrave of <hi>Hess:</hi> he despoil'd the Dukes of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi> and <hi>Cleves</hi> of their Territories, and form'd a great number of other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits of the same nature in <hi>Germany.</hi> He was Emperor, and King of <hi>Spain</hi> at the same time. The Limits of his Empire extended even to the New World: He possess'd the Seventeen Provinces entire: He was Master of <hi>Burgundy, Franche Contè,</hi> and <hi>Alsatia:</hi> He had an absolute Power over the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy:</hi> He had made an Accommodation with the Protestants. He had marry'd his Son <hi>Philip</hi> the II. with <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> And because he would not be expos'd to the good Fortune of <hi>Henry</hi> the II. who succeeded his Father <hi>Francis</hi> the I. he made a Truce with him for Five Years.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless, in the midst of the greatest Security that a Monarch could enjoy, he resign'd both his Empire and all his other Dominions. Now, Sir, compare the Conquests and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses of this great Monarch, with those of your Father; but above all, consider him in his voluntary Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35027:22"/> and compare that Condition of his with the present Condition of your Father. You must agree, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. is much inferiour to <hi>Charles</hi> the V. and that he has more reason, by a great deal, to resign his Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that it would be a lasting Honour to him to imitate the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a Prince so much his Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour.</p>
               <p>Thô the King be the proudest Prince in the World, there are a great number of Courtiers about him, who flatter him, That how powerful soever his Enemies may be, yet he is much more puissant than they; and that he shall ruin them at last, thô they should not destroy one another by their own Misunderstandings. Nevertheless, I am perswaded, that if he would but seriously consider the Reasons and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples which I have laid before him, they would very much stagger his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions. The greatest Pride in the World will stoop, when unavoidable Dangers stares it in the Face. And therefore let him be the proudest Prince in <hi>Europe,</hi> it behoves him to consider Events, and examine such
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35027:23"/> Proposals as are made him, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent those Accidents that may sully his Reputation in the Opinion of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity.</p>
               <p>Never believe, Sir, that the King will take it ill at your hands, if you propose him a way to preserve his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and his Crown, and save his People, of whom he is the Father. He will hearken to ye, never doubt it: And perhaps it may so fall out, that opening his Eyes to your Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strances, and shutting his Ears to the flattering Stories of his Courtiers, who have extoll'd him for those things, which he knows will one day be a Blot to his History, he will resolve to resign the Soveraignty into your hands, for fear of hazarding the loss of it, and seeing it under the Power of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>If the King loves you, as I make no question but he does, your Interest alone will move him, thô his own Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Safety of his People were not able to prevail with him. He will consider that his Misfortunes will be yours, and that the same Fate will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal him, as befel our first Parent,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35027:23"/> who envelopp'd in his own Misery all that descended from his Loyns.</p>
               <p>I know that Men at this day distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish between the Monarchy of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. and the <hi>Crown of France;</hi> that is, between the Usurpations of <hi>France,</hi> and the Ancient Patrimony of the Crown. I know that <hi>Historians</hi> most incens'd against the King, at the same time that they animate all the Princes and States of <hi>Europe</hi> to destroy the Monarchy, exhort 'em not to meddle with the Crown. But who knows, whether the Confederates will understand this Distinction, when they get the Mastery; or if they did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it, whither they would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Directions.</p>
               <p>Never flatter yourself, Sir, Policy is not govern'd by the Maxims of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity; and this you find to be Truth at home. Besides, there are certain Occasions when the Rights of War require that all should be taken from the Usurper, and that the Child, thô Innocent, should bear the Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Father.</p>
               <p>This one Argument will sway with the King. He will not run the risque
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35027:24"/> of seeing you vagabonding from one Court to another to beg, like a poor Wretch, a small Pension for Subsist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. He will leave you the Master of a Crown, which he has worn but too long, and will put himself among the Fathers of <hi>Mount Carmel,</hi> in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one of his Mistresses, the best beloved of 'em all, who now lives re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired after such a godly and devout manner, that all good People make no question, but that her Illustrious Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence will one day crown her with a <hi>Saintship.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="discourse">
               <head>The Second Discourse.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I May very well deceive myself: For in regard that Kings who have been prosperous, and are not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fallen from their Prosperity, do not always act as they ought, by the Rules of prudent Policy; how great soever the Dangers may be to which
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35027:24"/> they see themselves expos'd; it may happen that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. intoxica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Prosperity which has hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto attended him; wrapt up with the vast number of his Conquests, and pufft up with his numerous Armies; may perhaps take little care either of his own, or your Honour, nor the good of his Soul, meerly in hopes to die upon the Throne. There are Kings who hazard all, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are naturally inclin'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they are above all Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, but because they are so weak as to suffer themselves to be confirm'd in their Delusions by Flattery. This is the true Character of <hi>Lewis the Great.</hi> He believes that Fortune is a Goddess that is oblig'd always to court him; and that the Sun by which he usually represents himself in ordinary <hi>Impresses,</hi> is not like the natural Sun, that many times is Ecclips'd; and that because his Flatterers never cease to tell him, That he is as much above all other Kings, as other Princes are above their People, which makes him despise the Kings of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> for these Reasons I say, he believes himself to be more
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35027:25"/> Valiant and Couragious than either of those Hero's, who have signaliz'd themselves by so many renowned Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits.</p>
               <p>I am perswaded also, Sir, that the King believes himself to be the justest of all the Monarchs in the World, and looks upon the Confederates as Usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that would wrest his Patrimony from him.</p>
               <p>But in regard we are naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to believe what is most for our advantage, what is it you would have the King to believe? His Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers perswade him, That he has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Alsatia</hi> by force of Arms, in a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful War, and that he is become the true Possessor of it by several Treaties: That <hi>Christina Regent</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render'd <hi>Pignerol</hi> into his hands, to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for the excessive Expences he had been at in defending her against the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and her Brother's-in-Law: That he was constrain'd by <hi>Reason of State</hi> to make himself Master of <hi>Orange,</hi> and to demolish the Castle and Walls; his Conscience not permitting him to suffer a Place to stand in the heart of his Kingdom, which might afford any
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35027:25"/> Refuge to the Hereticks: That he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys <hi>Lorrain</hi> by a solemn Treaty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at <hi>Paris</hi> with Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> in the Year 1660: That <hi>Dunkirk</hi> was yielded up to him the same Year, by <hi>Charles</hi> the II.: That he seiz'd upon <hi>Franche Contè,</hi> at a time when he was in War with <hi>Spain,</hi> and that afterwards the possession was confirmed to him by the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen:</hi> That all the Places which he took in <hi>Flanders</hi> are but a small part of the lawful pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensions of his Queen: That <hi>Stras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> was surrender'd into his hands by the Magistrates of the City, for Reasons alledg'd at <hi>Munster,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated at <hi>Nimeghen:</hi> That <hi>Casal</hi> was given up to him the same day, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Violence offer'd: That the City of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> belong'd to him, as a Dependency of the Country which had been granted to him by the Treaties of Peace: That the taking of <hi>Avignon</hi> was just, because it was to mortifie a Pope who had treated him like a younger Brother, who is the eldest Son of the Church: That he never invaded the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> till he found they took no Notice of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensions
<pb n="05" facs="tcp:35027:26"/> of his Sister-in-Law: That he had never taken <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Emperor broke his Word in not restoring it to the Bishop of <hi>Spiers</hi> as he was engag'd to do. And lastly, If he has burnt so many Cities and Towns, and wasted all before him with Fire and Sword, it was only to unheard of Hostilities, to incline the <hi>German</hi> Princes to Peace. All these things are told him, and he believes them, because the Delusions are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and advantageous to him.</p>
               <p>There is one thing nevertheless which ought to unseal his Eyes, which is, that the same Flatterers, who would make him to be lookt upon as a just Prince, are the same Persons who have so often told him, He was the most Godly and Pious of Princes, at the same time that he most abandon'd himself to Debauchery; and that there never was any King in the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy, that ever had a juster Right to the Title of Most Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian King, thô at the same time he wag'd War against St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the most Sacred Laws which Christianity preaches to us; and that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35027:26"/> he made a League with an Infidel Prince to extirminate the Christians.</p>
               <p>A clear-sighted Prince would give little ear to such absurd and gross Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrick-Mongers. But Kings are weak, in this point; as are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est part of Men, and more especially <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. Labour therefore to disabuse him: There is no other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacle in your way.</p>
               <p>So long as the King believes himself Potent; so long as he flatters himself, That there is not any Prince in the World that can equal him in Worth and Merit. So long as he is fully perswaded, that all his Usurpations are lawful Conquests, and that his Rapines are just, he will never quit the Throne, till Death constrains him to a Resignation. But if he could once see that his Forces are impar'd, that he is not the only Hero of this Age; but that he has contaminated both his Life and his Reign, with an infinite number of unjust Actions, and by Hostilities, of which a <hi>Mahometan</hi> Prince would have been asham'd, he may then recollect himself, and resign to you a Scepter, which he is no longer fit to weild.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:35027:27"/>
               <p>I know very well it is the Maxim of some Men, <hi>That to undeceive a Man biassed by Prejudice, is to do him as ill a Turn, as that which was done to the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian <hi>Fool, who was made believe, that all the Vessels which arriv'd in that Port belong'd to him.</hi> But you must do him this bad Office, since you cannot do him a better. Tell him the Story of <hi>Darius,</hi> who was despoil'd of all his Dominions by <hi>Alexander,</hi> thô he were the greatest Prince that ever govern'd <hi>Persia.</hi> That of the Emperor <hi>Valeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> of whose back the <hi>Parthian Sapor</hi> made use for a Block to get up a Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back. Tell him that of <hi>Tomambey, Soldan</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> who after he had been dragg'd along upon the ground, at the Tail of an old <hi>Camel,</hi> was hang'd upon the next Tree. Mind him of <hi>Bajazet,</hi> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who was by <hi>Tamberlane</hi> King of the <hi>Tartars</hi> shut up, and carri'd about in a Iron Cage, where after he had liv'd above twenty Years, not having any other means to end his Life, he was forc'd to knock out his Brains against the Bars of the Cage. Make him understand that it concerns his Honour, his own
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35027:27"/> and your Interest, and the Interest of his Kingdom, for him to abandon willingly a Dignity, which it would be dishonourable for to relinquish by force; and that there is no Victory like vanquishing himself. And if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all that you can do, he will not be disabus'd, nor willingly resign to you his Royal Authority, I must then tell ye in down-right terms, you must make use of force, and take your measures so well, that you may ascend the Throne, after you have declared him unfit for Government.</p>
               <p>Upon this occasion, Sir, you must appear a <hi>Hero,</hi> and throw aside all your mortal Imbecillities. Upon this occasion it is, that you must call to mind, that there are certain Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances which may justifie a Son's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning of his own Father, without a Crime; nay, which will make it criminal not to take that course.</p>
               <p>Forget for a little time, your rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your Father, that you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your relation to <hi>France.</hi> Cast off those Tendernesses of a Child, that will oppose your Design. 'Tis a feeble Soul that will listen to Nature upon
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35027:28"/> such occasions. What! is there not the Ruin of a Nation; the Destruction of one of the fairest and most flourishing Kingdoms in the World; an Enemy wasting all before him; an Enemy Triumphant and Victorious! a Throne ranvers'd; a Royal Family dispers'd! All these things, do they not croud before your Eyes? And are not the dreadful Apparitions of such dire Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities enough to move ye, and make you in a moment forget that you are the Son of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV.</p>
               <p>When the Saviour of the World said, that we ought to hate Father and Mother for the love of him; and that he that does it not, deserves not to be call'd his Disciple; Does he not teach us in express Terms that the love which we ought to have for those that gave us being, is one of those Duties which may be sometimes dispens'd with? And that there are certain Occasions, and certain Necessities wherein Religion and Conscience o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige us to use our Parents no better than Pagans or Publicans. Now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what occasion, I beseech ye, can you more advantageously put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35027:28"/> this Precept of Christ, then when the Safety of a Nation lies at stake, and that you see it visibly upon the brink of Perdition.</p>
               <p>Had you no other then Chimerical Reasons, like that same <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yphron</hi> in <hi>Plato,</hi> who sues his Father, for having suffer'd one of his Slaves to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the bottom of a Dungeon, who had kill'd another, you might look upon <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. as a <hi>Sacred</hi> Person, as the Anointed of the Lord, as a Saint, whom it were not lawful for you so much as to touch. But the Reasons you have to the contrary are essential Reasons, since you cannot use him as Fathers are usually treated, unless you run the hazard of losing a Kingdom, which looks upon you in its Miseries, as her only Redeemer, and that you cannot without committing a great Crime, refuse to defend her, since it is in your Power to do it.</p>
               <p>Should you suffer Nature to work, I must confess your tenderness would appear praise-worthy, and would be the Subject of many Elogies, which the Priests would bestow upon yee: But how Cruel would it be! how unjust!
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35027:29"/> how unseasonable! Is it not better that one should perish, then that a whole Kingdom should be destroyed? Never Hesitate then, but let <hi>Lewis</hi> be the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim. 'Tis only by the means of such an Oblation, that you can Attone so many Princes, who have conspired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>France.</hi> He is the <hi>Jonas</hi> that must be thrown Overboard, if you will asswage the Tempest, and stop the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Thunder just ready to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> laid <hi>Saturn</hi> in Chains, and yet he was numbred among the Gods, nay look't upon as the chiefest, and Parent of all the Rest, notwithstanding he was so severe and harsh to him that gave him Being. You know what the Poets say of him. They tell yee that <hi>Saturn</hi> devour'd his own Children, and that it was for that Reason that his Son resolv'd to load him with Chains, not being able otherwise to put a stop to the brutish Fury of such an unnatural Father. The Morals of these Fables farther instruct you, that <hi>Saturn</hi> was a Prince that raigned among the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> that he became a Tyrant, and to defray his immoderate Expences, he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35027:29"/> had ruin'd his People, and that his Son dethron'd him, not being able to stop the Career of his Tyranny.</p>
               <p>This Example, you see, is as ancient as the Deluge. 'Tis true that Nature in those remote Ages, as well as now, taught us that common Precept, <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother.</hi> But that was no Hindrance, but that at the same time she inculcated into Children, that there were extraordinary Occasions which justified the dispensing with that Precept; and shews us that a Father, who is a Tyrant, is not to be lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Father, but as a furious Lion, who ought to be chained up by his Son. In a word, Nature inspires us to extirpate Tyranny, and that he who has a right to do it, ought not to be stupified or quelled with the Relation which he may have to the Tyrant. This is a Law in all Countries, and a Sanction in all Ages.</p>
               <p>Read the Eastern Histories, and you will there find a great number of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whose Destinies were like to that of <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Fourth, dethron'd in our days.</p>
               <p>But what need we search for Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35027:30"/> of this Nature among the Infidels, when we may find so many among the Christians. Surely, Sir, you need but cast your Eyes upon the Histories of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Swedeland,</hi> which are full of Examples of Princes dethron'd.</p>
               <p>The Emperour <hi>Maurice,</hi> who by the Report of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> was so zealous to defend the Catholick Faith, and to whom <hi>Euticheus</hi> of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and Abbot <hi>Theodore,</hi> had fortetold by Inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from Heaven, his Advancement to the Empire, yet forgot himself to that degree, that he commanded that no Souldier should turn Monk, till he had serv'd out his full time in the Wars. And to this Injustice, he added an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice so sordid, as rendred him odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all the Army. For having one day refused to redeem certain Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that had been taken in Battel, tho' the Ransom offered were very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable, the Officers and Souldiers by joynt Consent elected in his room <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas,</hi> tho' no more than a private Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion. Which <hi>Phocas</hi> pursued and took, and put him to death upon a publick Scaffold, after he had kill'd four of his Sons.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:35027:30"/>
               <p>The Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. to whom all the Historians give the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Heroick Prince, and who to omit those other noble Qualities that enrich'd his Mind, had been personal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in above sixty Battels, nevertheless had an infinite number of Faults, which cost him the loss of the Empire. For in his time, as well you know it was, that the famous quarrel began between the Popes and the Emperours. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the II. had cited him to <hi>Rome</hi> to give an accompt of his loose Life, and for his selling the Investitures of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, which he pretended to be his Right; but the Emperour derided his Citation. <hi>Gregory</hi> the VII. who suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Alexander,</hi> enraged at <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth's Contempt of the Holy See, and being willing to lay hold upon any pretence, treated him with so much scorn upon the occasion of Investitures, that the Emperour, who was no less haughty, observ'd no Measures with the Pope. He leagu'd himself with all his Enemies, and thereby drew upon himself an Excommunication, which was the cause of all his Misfortunes. 'Tis true, that he in like manner Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35027:31"/> the Pope in an Assembly of the Bishops and all the Ecclesiastical Princes of the Empire. But <hi>Henry</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless, in a short time after, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to that extremity, that seeing that most of the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> had taken Arms against him, at the sollicitation of <hi>Gregory,</hi> he resolv'd to go a Penitent to <hi>Rome,</hi> to take off his Excommunication, which in truth the Pope did, but in such a scornful manner, that all the Princes and States of <hi>Italy</hi> murmur'd at it. For <hi>Henry</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrived at <hi>Canossa,</hi> where the Pope lay, they let him enter the first Gate, having there enclosed him all alone, while they that attended him were left without, he was given to understand that there was no Remission to be had, unless he fasted three days together, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less he stood every one of those days till the evening, in the Snow, upon his bare feet, and after that Penance im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored the Pope's Pardon for his Fault: all which was punctually performed.</p>
               <p>This Prince, who never expected so severe an Entertainment, incens'd at his own folly that had constrain'd him to be reduc'd to a necessity so violent,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35027:31"/> joyned in Opinion with the Princes and States of <hi>Italy,</hi> who lookt upon the Pope's pride, as a thing of dangerous Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and declared himself once more an Enemy to the Pope. But the Issue proved unsuccessful. For <hi>Gregory</hi> by his secret Intrigues, having brought over all the Princes to his side, he was deprived of his Imperial Dignity, and <hi>Rodolphus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Suabia,</hi> was elected in his room, and Crown'd at <hi>Mayence</hi> in the Year 1077.</p>
               <p>The Emperour on the other side, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared War against <hi>Rodolphus,</hi> and foil'd him several times; but in regard the Bishops, who had elected the latter, were obliged to support him, they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised the Pope to Excommunicate <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> a second time; which he did: and then it was that <hi>Rodolphus</hi> received the Crown from the Hands of <hi>Gregory</hi> with these words:
<q>
                     <l>Petra dedit <hi>Petro, Petrus</hi> Diadema <hi>Rodolpho▪</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From Petra <hi>Peter</hi> first receiv'd his Name,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Ralph</hi> consigns the Diademe.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperour on the other side, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving assembled a Councel of several Bishops, both of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and presiding himself in the Assembly, as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35027:32"/> his Predecessors had done, <hi>Gregory</hi> the VII. was there deposed, and <hi>Gilbert,</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Ravenna,</hi> who call'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self <hi>Clement</hi> the III. was chosen in his room. But soon after <hi>Rodolphus</hi> was wounded in a Battel which he fought, and dyed of his wounds. He was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred with great Pomp, and upon his Tomb was engrav'd a Crown, with all the other Imperial Ornaments; which gave occasion to <hi>Henry</hi> to say, <hi>That he wish'd all his Enemies enterr'd as magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently as</hi> Rodolphus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> being rid of his Rival, prepared for a Voyage into <hi>Italy,</hi> where he made himself Master of <hi>Rome,</hi> where he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Pope and himself to be crown'd with all the usual Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless, in regard this War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Henry</hi> and the <hi>Apostolick See</hi> had troubled all <hi>Germany,</hi> and that all the Princes were oblig'd to take part with the Head of the Church, all the World leagu'd themselves against the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and principally his two Sons <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade</hi> and <hi>Henry,</hi> who entred into a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to Depose him, to the end they might restore Peace to <hi>Germany,</hi> and at the same time rid the Holy See of one
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35027:32"/> of the most implacable Enemies that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Popes had.</p>
               <p>In a word, <hi>Henry</hi> the Son took him Prisoner, and having summon'd an As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of the Princes to <hi>Mayence,</hi> and the Pope's Legates, who were there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, having read over the two Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications that had been thundred out against the Emperour, the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with one Consent depos'd him from the Imperial Dignity, and proclaim'd his Son <hi>Henry.</hi> After which the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops of <hi>Mayence</hi> and <hi>Cologne,</hi> with the Bishop of <hi>Wertembergh,</hi> were deputed to carry the News to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, and to bring away the Imperial Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> urg'd many strong Reasons, and did his utmost to oppose this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign; but the Bishops by violence took away the Crown which they had put upon his Head, and by force disrob'd him of the Imperial Mantle, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to <hi>Mayence,</hi> delivered them to the new Emperour: Nor could <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. be ever again restored.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wenceslaus</hi> Emperour and King of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> at the Age of seventeen years, took upon him the Government of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35027:33"/> Empire and Kingdom of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> but he brought along with him such vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conditions, that worse could not be. He kept his Residence at <hi>Prague,</hi> the Capital City of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the example of <hi>Charles</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he sold what was to be sold of the Rights of the Empire, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a number of other Miscarriages, which were the occasion of a Civil War in <hi>Germany,</hi> which proved fatal to several Princes.</p>
               <p>Besides, one great piece of Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence which <hi>Wenceslaus</hi> committed in the management of his Affairs, he was addicted to so much Debauchery of all sorts, that he was contemn'd by all his Subjects. More especially he drew up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himself their hatred by his excessive Impositions which he laid upon them, and by the unheard of Cruelties which he exercised upon their Persons, to which he had habituated himself in such a manner, that he made no scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to cut off the Heads of Magistrates of <hi>Prague,</hi> without any Legal Trial.</p>
               <p>The great Lords of <hi>Bohemia</hi> seeing these Disorders of their King increase from day to day, thought it but neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35027:33"/> to put a stop to them, and by the consent of <hi>Sigismund</hi> the King's Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they confin'd him in a close Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, from whence he found a way to escape, about four Months after. He was afterward taken and retaken several times, till at length having made his last Escape, he got to <hi>Prague,</hi> and by the Assistance of some Lords that were his Friends, he re-assumed his Royal Authority, with promise to lead a more regular Life for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless, he took no more care of the Affairs of the Empire than he did before. He sold the <hi>Seignioral</hi> Rights of several Lands, and the Title of D. of <hi>Milan,</hi> without the Consent or Knowledge of the Electors and other Princes. So that the Princes perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the ways he could to dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Empire to supply his sordid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, and this at a time that the <hi>Wicklevians</hi> began to divide it, and that the Victorious Turks prevailed over the Christians every day; These Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I say, after long forbearances, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it concern'd the Publick Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to delay no longer the electing an
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35027:34"/> Emperour capable to restore the Peace of the Empire, and support the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Dignity, by the Advice of Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> declared <hi>Wenceslaus</hi> uncapable to Govern, and Deposed him.</p>
               <p>This Sentance of Deposal was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished the Twentieth of <hi>August,</hi> 1400. <hi>Frederick</hi> Duke of <hi>Lunenburgh</hi> and <hi>Brunswick</hi> was in Nomination, but he dying within a few days, <hi>Robert,</hi> sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the Little, was elected in his room.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Winceslaus</hi> seemed to be insensible of his being deposed; and it is reported that he should say, <hi>That he was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd to be discharg'd of the Burthen of the Empire, in hopes that he might the better apply himself to the Government of his Kingdom.</hi> And indeed for Nineteen years that he reigned afterward in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> his Subjects found his Conduct infinitely much more rational than it had been before. And thus you see, Sir, that the Deposing a Prince may some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prove a meritorious Work, at which the Angels themselves rejoyce. For in short, not only a whole Estate is thereby preserved, but you contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Salvation of a reprobate and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35027:34"/> ungracious Prince, who is thereby snatch'd, as I may say, from the jaws of Hell, to be translated into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise, and made a Vessel of Election.</p>
               <p>Fathers are oblig'd, according to the Maxims of the Gospel, to watch over the Salvation of their Children; and the Scripture says, <hi>That he who neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects the care of his Family, is worse than an Infidel.</hi> On the other side, Children are no less oblig'd, in respect of those that gave them Being. They ought to be the Fathers of their Fathers, and are oblig'd to labour their Salvation, when they see them in the Road to Perdition. They are responsible for their Souls, when they may contribute to their Salvation and do not do it. Would you, Sir, acquire the Name of <hi>Pious?</hi> save a Father, who like <hi>Wence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slaus,</hi> has endeavoured so long time the Ruin of his Kingdom. Save a Father, whose Life, like that of <hi>Wenceslaus,</hi> has been but one continued Wolf of Cruelties and Debaucheries. Lastly, Sir, save a Father, who has been guilty of a thousand more Miscarriages than ever that effeminate Prince.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:35027:35"/>
               <p>Were it possible to save him by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stings, by Mortifications, by Sacrifices, it behoves you to spare for nothing of that Nature. You ought to make Vows to all the Saints, to make an Interest in the Queen of Heaven by Devotions extraordinary, gird your self with Sack-cloth, and go in Pilgrimages round about the World in search of some prevailing Relique yet unknown. But alas! you would in vain condemn your flesh to such a sort of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Ambition, Breach of Faith, Luxury, Cruelty, and all other Vices of this Nature, so predominant in your Father, are a sort of Devils not to be expelled by Fastings nor Prayers. You must tear the Crown from his Head; You must ranverse his Throne; You must seize upon his Scepter. <hi>Wence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slaus</hi> had been always <hi>Wenceslaus,</hi> had he been always Emperour. Have you less affection for <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. than the Subjects of <hi>Wenceslaus</hi> had for a <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danapalus?</hi> For a Prince that was so unworthy to sit upon the Throne of the <hi>Caesars?</hi> No, Sir, you love the King too well, not to furnish him with the means of his Conversion. You must
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35027:35"/> deprive him of that Soveraignty which he has so long abus'd to the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of all his Kingdom. You must despoil him of that Royal Dignity, which is so great an Obstacle of his Salvation. You must shut him up in a Monastery, where he may attend the work of his Mortification, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of so many Saints, who have voluntarily confin'd themselves to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entangle themselves from the snares of the World, and gain Paradise. Or if it be a Crown he so much wants, you may procure him one more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than any Celestial Diadem; for who shall hinder you? For who will hinder you from adorning him with a shaven Crown?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. would not be the first King that has been depos'd in <hi>France. Childeric,</hi> who was the third King af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Pharamond,</hi> having at the same mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he ascended the Throne, abused his Royal Authority, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded. The <hi>French</hi> could not endure that a young King, not content to load them with Taxes, should Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand their Wives and Daughters from them. Therefore they assembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35027:36"/> with a Resolution to oppose his Tyranny; and after they had declar'd him unworthy to wield the <hi>Scepter,</hi> they elected in his room, <hi>Egidius,</hi> or <hi>Giles,</hi> who commanded for the <hi>Romans</hi> in <hi>Gaul,</hi> and resided at <hi>Soissons. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deric</hi> submitted to his Deposal, and lived in the Kingdom like a private person; but perceiving there was some Design against his Life, he fled for Sanctuary to King <hi>Basin</hi> in <hi>Turingia,</hi> from whence he was recalled some time after, and restored to his Throne, <hi>Egidius</hi> being expelled for his Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thierry</hi> King of <hi>Neustria</hi> and <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> after he had raigned somewhat more than a year, was shaved and sent to the Monastery of <hi>St. Dennis,</hi> where he remained, till <hi>Childeric</hi> II. who was advanced in his room, was put to death by his own Subjects for his Cruelties and Debaucheries, and then was again fetched out of the Abby, to reassume the Government, from which he had been deposed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Childeric</hi> III. called the Madman, who was the last King of the first Race, tasted of the same Destiny with
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35027:36"/>
                  <hi>Childeric</hi> I. and <hi>Thierry.</hi> For in regard he was a Prince incapable to hold the Reins of Government by reason of his folly and stupidity, <hi>Pepin</hi> assembled a Parliament, that would have presently conferred the Title of King upon him, but that they were forced to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to the Pope to absolve them from their Oath of Allegiance.</p>
               <p>The Pope at that time was <hi>Zachary;</hi> to whom <hi>Burchard</hi> Bishop of <hi>Bourges</hi> was sent; who represented to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness the sad Condition of <hi>France,</hi> the disposition of the <hi>French,</hi> and the incapacity of the King, who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately granted him a Dispensation as was desired.</p>
               <p>Which being brought from <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> assembled another Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Soissons,</hi> where they deposed <hi>Childeric,</hi> and elected <hi>Pepin</hi> in his place. <hi>Boniface,</hi> Arch-Bishop of <hi>Mayence,</hi> was present at that Assembly, with several other Bishops; and by the same De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree which deposed <hi>Childeric,</hi> he was first condemned to be shaved, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards confin'd to the Abby of <hi>St. Bertin</hi> near <hi>St. Omers,</hi> from whence he was removed to the Monastery of <hi>St.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35027:37"/> Hemeran</hi> at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> where he dyed a <hi>Monk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pepin</hi> II. having rendred himself odious to his Kingdom, by his Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, Injustice, and Debauchery, the Lords of <hi>Aquitain</hi> called in <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Bald</hi> his <hi>Uncle,</hi> who was received at <hi>Limoges</hi> with all the Expressions of Joy imaginable, and by all the Lords at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to the Siege of <hi>Tholose,</hi> which he took by Composition. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less <hi>Charles,</hi> as unjust as naturally he was, made a scruple of dethroning his Nephew, which occasioned a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation between them. After which, <hi>Pepin</hi> by his ill Management provoked the <hi>Aquitains</hi> to that degree, that they seized upon him, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him to <hi>Charles</hi> his Uncle, who caused him to be shaved, and then shut him up in the Monastery of <hi>St. Medard</hi> at <hi>Soissons.</hi> True it is, he found a way to escape, and sculk'd about for some time, and not knowing what Course to take, at length cast himself upon the <hi>Normans,</hi> which only serv'd to make him more odious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible than he was before. So that being retaken, his own Subjects look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35027:37"/> upon him as a Traytor to this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and to Christendom, condemned him to death; however they sav'd his Life, and penn'd him up in the strong Castle of St. <hi>Lis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Gross,</hi> who was Emperour and King of <hi>France,</hi> both at a time, a most prosperous Prince at the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Reign, became at length the most unfortunate of Men. He was at first ador'd by the People, for the great and glorious Atchievements that had signaliz'd his Prowess. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd out of <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Sarasins</hi> that threatned <hi>Rome.</hi> After that, he raised a great Army to oppose the Excursions of the <hi>Normans.</hi> But in regard that Princes are not always prosperous, and for that he found a greater Resistance than he did in <hi>Italy,</hi> he was overthrown in one Battel; upon which, fearing doubtless, the event of a second, he concluded a Peace with the Enemy, by which he yielded to them the possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>Friesland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Concession disgusted the <hi>French,</hi> as well for that <hi>Charles</hi> had no Right or Authority to make it without their Consent, as because by quitting those
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35027:38"/> two Provinces to the <hi>Normans,</hi> he had dismembred the Royal Patrimony, which could not be alienated by the Constitutions of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>One would have thought that the Necessity to which <hi>Charles</hi> was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, might have in some measure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused him. But being from that time lookt upon as a Prince very imperious, and more then that, as a Prince un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, for contemning and ill treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a people, that had so much contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to his Advancement to the Throne, the <hi>French</hi> conceived so great an Aversion against him as would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no Reconciliation.</p>
               <p>Some say that <hi>Charles</hi> had always a crackt Brain, ever since a supposal of his, that he had been the Devil, who put a thousand whims in his Head touching the Empress his Wife. Which caused him to be guilty of a thousand Impertinencies. So that after he had committed a number of Extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in an Assembly at <hi>Tribur,</hi> the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest effects of a raving Brain, all his <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Bavarian</hi> Subjects aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned him, by the Advice of his own Sister <hi>Hildegard,</hi> to elect in his room
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35027:38"/>
                  <hi>Arnold,</hi> the Natural Son of his Brother. The <hi>Lorrainers</hi> also and <hi>Suabians</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the example of the <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Bavarians;</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> call'd in <hi>Eudes,</hi> Count of <hi>Paris,</hi> and Duke of <hi>France,</hi> who had nominated in the last <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Stammerer.</hi> So that <hi>Charles</hi> was all of a suddain left alone, without so much as a <hi>Lacquey</hi> to serve him, or any thing to subsist upon, like <hi>Belizarius</hi> the General of <hi>Justini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>'s Armies. Only <hi>Luitper</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Mayence,</hi> took pity of him; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd him for some time, till at lengt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Arnold,</hi> at the solicitation of the said Bishop, having allow'd the Revenue of two or three pitiful Villages, which he made choice of for his Retirement, where he ended his days after a very Tragical manner, being strangled by the People that attended on him, if we may give credit to History.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Simple,</hi> being recalled out of <hi>England,</hi> whither <hi>Adelaida</hi> his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had carried him, to avoid the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Carleman,</hi> the Natural Sons of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Stammerer,</hi> was crown'd at <hi>Rheims</hi> in the Year 893. and acknowledged by the <hi>French-Charles</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:35027:39"/> began his Reign, with a Peace concluded with the <hi>Normans,</hi> after he had got the better of them in several Conflicts. He seized upon almost all <hi>Lorrain;</hi> but he disposed so indiscreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Government, that those whom he entrusted made themselves Masters of it. Besides, he was a young Prince, of weak parts, and led by his Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites that absolutely possessed his Ears. So that his ill management of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Kingdom so highly incens'd the Lords of the Kingdom, that being assembled at <hi>Soissons,</hi> they expell'd him his Dominions, and reduc'd him to such extremity, that he was constrain'd to retire for Relief to <hi>Foulque</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Rheims,</hi> who had chiefly laboured his Admittance to the Crown; who maintain'd him at his own Charges, all his other Revenues being taken from him.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, <hi>Robert</hi> Count of <hi>Paris,</hi> Brother of <hi>Eudes,</hi> and Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father by the Father's side to <hi>Hugh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> caused himself to be crowned at St. <hi>Rheny</hi> by <hi>Rheimes.</hi> Thereupon <hi>Charles</hi> betook himself to <hi>Henry</hi> the III. who promised to assist him. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35027:39"/> the Emperor's Succors arriv'd, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> was at the Head of a great Army, and gave <hi>Charles</hi> Battel near <hi>Soissons,</hi> wherein he was slain; and some say that <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Simple</hi> ran him through with his Lance. However it were, <hi>Charles</hi> made so ill use of his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that his Enemies gain'd time to oppose against him <hi>Raoul</hi> of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheless, <hi>Charles</hi>'s Army increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and certain it is, that <hi>Raoul</hi> at first began to fear him. But the weak King, when he should have hazarded all to have made himself King by force of Arms, made Suit for a Peace, which was his ruin. For <hi>Herbert,</hi> Count of <hi>Vermandois,</hi> Son in Law to <hi>Robert,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drawn him to St. <hi>Quintins,</hi> under pretence of consulting about the Peace, there seiz'd upon him, and sent him to <hi>Castle Thierry,</hi> from whence being brought to <hi>Soissons,</hi> where at the same time the principal Lords of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom were assembled, he was solemnly Deposed, and <hi>Raoul</hi> as solemnly elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his room. <hi>Charles</hi> was removed from Prison to Prison, and dyed after he had reigned thirty years from his Coronation to his Imprisonment.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:35027:40"/>
               <p>The Exclusion of <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> after the Extinction of the second Race by the Death of <hi>Lewis</hi> the V. was a real Deposal; as you must allow, Sir, if you mark well the History.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> was the Son of <hi>Lewis</hi> the IV. Brother to <hi>Lothairr,</hi> and Uncle to <hi>Lewis</hi> the V. Now the Throne being void by the Death of the last King, by the Law of the Land, the Crown ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently belonged to the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> being the first Prince of the Royal Blood. Nevertheless you know, Sir, that <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi> the Son of <hi>Hugh</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> Master of the Palace, and Count of <hi>Paris,</hi> was establisht King, &amp; <hi>Charles</hi> excluded.</p>
               <p>Certain it is, that the General Estates of <hi>France</hi> had reason sufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Duke of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> for besides that, the Crown of <hi>France</hi> was not then properly successive, the young Duke did all he could to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self unworthy of the Dignity.</p>
               <p>For first, he attended the Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> the II. to be by him invested in the Dutchy of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> and did him Homage for it, instead of holding it in Soveraignty, as he might have done. Which the <hi>French</hi> could not but look
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35027:40"/> upon as a Cowardly Action, by which in a manner he resigned his Pretensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, after he was Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> he declared against <hi>France,</hi> and sided with the <hi>Germans</hi> that had withdrawn themselves from their Obedience to the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy.</p>
               <p>These two Considerations were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to render the Duke suspected to <hi>France,</hi> and consequently to make him be lookt upon as unworthy of the Soveraign Government. But that which more especially alienated the Minds of the <hi>French</hi> from him, and made them contemn and hate <hi>Charles,</hi> was his ill Conduct, his Cruelties and Tyranny. For tho' the <hi>Lorrainers</hi> were not his Natural Subjects, he cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed not to oppress and load them with Taxes to support the Expences of his Prodigality.</p>
               <p>So that when the Vacancy fell, the <hi>French</hi> made no scruple, to exclude him the Kingdom. For in all Exigencies of this Nature, the People, or those that represent them, having not only a <hi>Right</hi> to limit, restrain, and order the Circumstances of Successions as they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35027:41"/> shall judge most proper; but also to choose such a King as they please themselves, the <hi>States General</hi> assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Mayon</hi> to proceed according to the ancient Customes to the Election of a new Monarch, so soon as the Posture of Affairs would permit them. All the Persons of Note and Rank throughout the Kingdom there met; and most certain it is, Sir, that there was never seen in <hi>France</hi> an Assembly of that Nature so noble, nor so nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> was then in <hi>Germany,</hi> and in regard he could not choose how the <hi>French</hi> stood affected toward him, he sent his Ambassadors to the Assembly, who declared in their Master's Name, That if they cast their Eyes upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and did not Elect him, seeing he was the presumptive Heir, and first Prince of the Blood, he would make them obey him, and choose him by force.</p>
               <p>The <hi>States,</hi> no way pleased with this <hi>Harangue,</hi> nor minding the Duke's Threats, were about to have stopt his Ambassadors, in order to have made them pay for the rashness of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35027:41"/> But in regard they thought it not convenient to violate the Law of Nations, they thought it sufficient to send him an Answer full of scorn and derision, and at the same time by a solemn Sentence declar'd, That since <hi>Charles</hi> had shewn himself a Friend to the Enemies of <hi>France,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> had renounc'd his Friendship; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, that he had forfeited the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Law, as well for being the first that broke it, as for that they were not bound to acknowledge for King, the sworn Enemy of their Country. And therefore, since their Oath oblig'd them to a King that was to be lookt upon as the Father of his Country, to a just, prudent, mild, and moderate Prince, they protested their open re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing him before God, with a safe Conscience, and without any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Fundamental Law; and declar'd withall, that their Intention was to choose a King that should take care of the Repose of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>This Declaration was deliver'd to the Embassadors, with a particular Command forthwith to depart the Kingdom: And the same day by an
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35027:42"/> Authentic Edict it was concluded, That since there was a necessity to choose a King for the Preservation of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and the Line being extinct by the death of <hi>Lewis</hi> V. and the manifest Felony of <hi>Charles</hi> D. of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> they did sincerely Elect <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> for King, and promised to obey both him and his Posterity, as their Lawful Kings, according to the Laws of the Kingdom, as they were bound in Duty to God and their own Consciences.</p>
               <p>This Edict being published, <hi>Hugh</hi> was Crown'd at <hi>Reims</hi> by the Arch-Bishop <hi>Adalberon;</hi> not one that were present at <hi>Noyon,</hi> or at <hi>Capet</hi>'s Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion making the least Challenge in <hi>Charles</hi>'s behalf, but on the contrary, subscribing the Oath in Writing, as well as swearing it by word of Mouth to <hi>Hugh Capet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some say, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the V. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed the Kingdom to <hi>Hugh</hi> by Will; others, that he left it to his Wife by his last Testament, to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render it back to <hi>Hugh,</hi> upon Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he should Marry her: and so it was not by Choice, but by Will, that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35027:42"/> this first King of the third Race came to the Crown. But as <hi>Mezerai,</hi> who was one of the best Historians of his Age, observes, <hi>His strongest Title was the general Consent of the People of France.</hi> For, Sir, I would not have you flatter your self to think otherwise, but that the People, as they have an Original Right to create the Kings that are to Govern them, so they have a Right to Depose and Exclude them from the Crown, when the Necessity and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of the Kingdom require it.</p>
               <p>I confess, Sir, that after the Reign of <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi> we do not find in our History any Example of Kings being depos'd. But would you know the Reason? Besides that this Third Race has had no such slothful and weak Princes as abound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in the preceding <hi>Lines;</hi> the Kings of <hi>France</hi> are become much more powerful since that, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Usurpt by degrees the Rights and Priviledges of the People. <hi>Hugh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> who first found the secret how to win the hearts of the <hi>French,</hi> was the first that began to eclipse the Right of Election, by causing his Son <hi>Robert</hi> to be Crowned with the Consent of the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35027:43"/> Estates of the Kingdom: And it came to pas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that afterwards his Successor sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensibly set themselves above the Laws, and now enjoy an unlimitted Power.</p>
               <p>Do you believe, Sir, that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>France</hi> are such Fools, as not to perceive, that the Kings of <hi>France</hi> Reign like Tyrants, and that their Subjects live like Slaves? They have complain'd of it a long time, they have bewail'd their Condition, they have murmured; and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey have not freed themselves as yet fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat Soveraign and Despotic Power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich makes their Monarchs Masters of their Lives and Estates, 'tis not because they could not; for when an Opportunity has presented it self to shake off so cruel a Yoke, there have been many Tumults and Insurrections, of which you have seen some in the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV.</p>
               <p>What think you the<note n="*" place="margin">At <hi>Paris</hi> a Toll-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer having deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a peny of an Herb-woman for a bunch of Water-cresses, the Rabble gather'd together, at the cries of the Woman, went and beat down the Gates of the City-Magazine to Arm thems<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lves, and there having gotten three or four thousand Iron Hammers, they were called by the Name of <hi>Malliotins,</hi> or People that knockt down People with Hammers.</note>
                  <hi>Malliotins</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35027:43"/> the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the VI. They would have seized upon the Throne, and taken the Government into their own hands, to have freed themselves from the heavy Taxes which the King had imposed upon the Kingdom, and upon all the <hi>Parisiens. Paris, Rouen, Troyes, Orleance,</hi> and several other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties took up Arms at the same time, in order to have broken their Chains. But <hi>Charles</hi> the VI. returning with a powerful Army out of <hi>Flanders,</hi> broke their Measures all of a sudden. They were afraid to incur the same Fate with those of the City of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> which the King had reduced, and put under the Power of <hi>Lewis de Marle</hi> their Count, after <hi>Philip D' Artevelle</hi> had engaged them in a Rebellion. The <hi>Parisians</hi> no less Proud, but not so Couragious as those of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> march'd forth above 30000 strong to meet <hi>Charles</hi> in the Plain of <hi>St. Dennis,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a shew as if they would have fought the King. But a sort of Pannick Terror falling upon them, they durst not enterprize any thing.</p>
               <p>That abominable Maxim, That a Tyrant and a Heretical Prince may
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35027:44"/> be Assassinated, which has been too often practised in <hi>France,</hi> since the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits grew numerous, is a convincing Argument that our People are under Bondage, and that they are ill satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the Government. For if they had in their hands the power which they had Originally, that is, were they powerful enough to Depose a Prince that oppresses and devours them, that forces from them their Wives and Daughters, that overwhelms them with Taxes and Contributions, that puts them to death unjustly, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for matters in Religion, or for Opinions which the Church condemns, they would never have been provoked to dye their hands in the Blood of the Lord's Anointed: The Church would never have had the sad occasion to see the most Sacred of her Maxims violated, <hi>That she abhors the Effusion of Blood.</hi> But what shall we do, Sir? This is the fruit of Tyranny and Arbitrary Power. The Peoples hands are ty'd; they cannot do what Lawfully they might; they discharge themselves of their sins by committing Crimes; and this ought to make all the Kings in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35027:44"/> the World tremble, that push on their Power too far. For in short, there are Villains, Mad-men, and Jesuits in every corner.</p>
               <p>I believe also, we might find several Kings that have seen themselves upon the very brink of being depriv'd of their Crowns: but I shall mention onely <hi>Henry</hi> the III. for I have that Prince in view, because he was kill'd by a<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>III.</hi> being gone to Besiege <hi>Paris</hi> with an Army of <hi>40000</hi> Men, a certain Monk, whose Name was <hi>Jacob Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> stabb'd him at <hi>St. Cloud's,</hi> with a Knife, in the lower part of the Belly, while he was Reading certain Letters, which the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nk delivered him, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muse him. The King dy'd next day of the Wound.</note>
                  <hi>Monk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry,</hi> who had already signaliz'd himself in several extraordinary Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, was elected King of <hi>Poland,</hi> after the Death of <hi>Sigismund Augustus,</hi> and was Crowned at <hi>Cracovia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But understanding the Death of <hi>Charles</hi> IX. his Brother, he withdrew himself secretly out of <hi>Poland,</hi> and was Crown'd King of <hi>France;</hi> at what time he found the Kingdom divided by the Factions of the <hi>Huguenots.</hi> Which Factions soon after dividing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three bulky Parties, the Contest
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35027:45"/> between them was call'd, The War of the <hi>Three Henrys.</hi> That of the <hi>League,</hi> under the Conduct of <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Guise;</hi> that of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> headed by <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>Navarr;</hi> and King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Party, which were called the <hi>Politicks,</hi> and was always the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Navar</hi> laid no present claim to the Crown, only desired to preserve the Succession in the right <hi>Channel,</hi> if the Branch of <hi>Valois</hi> should happen to fail. And he had reason for what he did; in regard that after the Death of the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the V. had declar'd him incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to enjoy it, as also the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> because they were both <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> But it was not so with the Duke of <hi>Guise:</hi> for in regard he was Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and that the Exclusion of of his <hi>Line</hi> by the <hi>Capets,</hi> still stuck in his stomach, he aspir'd to the Crown. And it was no fault of his, that <hi>Henry</hi> had not been depos'd several times; but all his Arts fail'd him. He had taken the King's side, that he might the better play his part, and secure the Crown to himself. And indeed, at
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35027:45"/> the very time that he seem'd to serve him most faithfully, and that he fought the <hi>Religionanes,</hi> in a Council held at <hi>Rome,</hi> (for that Court still favour'd his Designs) they did not stick to say, <q>That thô the Race of the <hi>Capets</hi> had succeeded to the Temporal Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of the Kingdom of <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maign,</hi> it had no Right of Successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Apostolick Benediction, affected and coveted by the Posterity of that great Prince. On the other side, that as <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> by usurping <hi>Charles</hi>'s Crown, had usurp'd the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction; he had thereby drawn upon himself, and his Successors, a perpetual Malediction, which had render'd his Posterity refractory and disobedient to the Church; as being introduc'd to ruin that damnable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror call'd by the <hi>French, The Liberty of the Gallican Church.</hi>
                  </q> To which they added in conclusion, <q>That if the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> could but arrive at his end, which was to extirminate the Hereticks, he might by the Warrant and Permission of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, shut up the King and Queen, in a Monastery, as <hi>Pepin</hi> his Predecessor had serv'd <hi>Childeric.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:35027:46"/>
               <p>And so far was the Party of the League from expecting less, that they averr'd it openly. They call'd the King, <hi>The Doubtful King of</hi> France <hi>and the Imaginary King of</hi> Poland. One day these Verses were found writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a Coal in the Chappel of the <hi>Blanes-Battus,</hi> in the<note n="*" place="margin">This was a Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of White Penitents, Instituted by <hi>Hen. 3.</hi> Of which Fraternity the greatest part of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites were. This Prince had given himself over to such a ridiculous sort of Bigottry, that he would sometimes run about the Streets of <hi>Paris</hi> all Night in Procession.</note>
                  <hi>Augustines</hi> of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Bones of the poor Saints deceas'd</l>
                  <l>In a <hi>Burgundian</hi> Cross here shown,</l>
                  <l>Declare that all thy Prayers are ceast,</l>
                  <l>And thou thy self shalt lose thy Crown.</l>
               </q>
               <p>One of his Engravers having finished the Quadrant of the Sun-Dial in the Palace, and having put over head these words:
<q>
                     <l>—Who gave thee Two</l>
                     <l>Before, a Triple-Crown shall give thee now.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Two days after, over the Door of a Shop near the Sun-Dial, this Answer was writ:
<q>The Third shall so be given him, as he the Second held before.</q> Which gave occasion to the following Distich:
<q>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:35027:46"/>
                     <l>Who gave thee Two, took One away, the other shakes,</l>
                     <l>The Third with Razor keen, the nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Barber makes.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And over the Motto of the Empress, which the King always bore, <hi>Manet ultima Coelo,</hi> were added these Verses:
<q>
                     <l>The heavy Pains for all thy Perjuries</l>
                     <l>Attend thee last of all above the Skies.</l>
                     <l>For God all Breakers of their Word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temns,</l>
                     <l>And low deprest to utmost Hell condemns.</l>
                     <l>Heaven owns thee not, no Crown can Tyrants claim;</l>
                     <l>Unless at last a shaven Crown with shame.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Even the very Preachers in their Pulpits publickly talked the same Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons. But this was not all; for to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate the Design which they had projected of enclosing him in a <hi>Cloyster,</hi> some were for seizing him while he made his Nocturnal Processions; some while he was <hi>Masquerading,</hi> which was a sport very common with him. Eight days before the famous Battel of the <hi>Barricado's,</hi> Madam <hi>de Montpensier</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given a Dinner to four or five <hi>Curiassers,</hi> in a House in the Country,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35027:47"/> without St. <hi>Anthony</hi>'s Gate, as the King was returning home with only four or five Lacqueys, and two Gentlemen, those Cuirassie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s were to have seiz'd and run away with him; and then it was to be given out, that the <hi>Hugenots</hi> had taken him. And you well know, Sir, that the Estates of <hi>Blois</hi> were as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled to no other purpose, but that the King might fall the more easily into the Hands of the Duke of <hi>Guize;</hi> and <hi>Madam de Monpensier</hi> carried the Scissars at her Girdle, that were to have cut off his Hair, in order to the making his Crown. But the King being inform'd of this Enterprize, caus'd the <hi>Duke,</hi> and the <hi>Cardinal</hi> his Brother to be both murder'd. And it was well it came into his mind; for without that expedient, he had been in great danger of dying a Priest.</p>
               <p>I need not tell you what had like to have happen'd to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. himself, in the time of the Prince's War, it being a thing which you know so well. The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was going to overturn the Throne, and if he prov'd unsuccessful, the King may thank the Religionaries, who would never forsake him.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:35027:47"/>
               <p>Know you, Sir, what would have happen'd had the Duke of <hi>Guize,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> attain'd their ends? They would have caused themselves to be crown'd Kings; and they would have receiv'd Embassadors from all parts, to congratulate their Restaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Thrones of their Ancestors. The Pope himself has sent a <hi>Nuncio</hi> to make them Partakers of the Apostolic <hi>Benediction,</hi> and to absolve the Subjects of <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Lewis,</hi> from their Oaths of Fidelity and Allegiance. And all the rest of the Christian Princes would not have fail'd to say, That <hi>Henry</hi> had drawn upon himself all his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, by his Leagues, by his Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, by his insane Biggottries, by his blind dotage upon his <hi>Minions,</hi> and that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. as much a God as they lookt upon him to be, ought to be deem'd no other, than the Son of <hi>Mazarine,</hi> or some other <hi>Stallion</hi> of the Queen's.</p>
               <p>But as for the Duke of <hi>Guise,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> they would have been accompted real Princes; they would have been acknowledg'd for lawful Princes, so soon as they had
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35027:48"/> been invested with the Regal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, thô it had been never so illegal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly usurp'd. They had made Alliances with them as <hi>France</hi> did with <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> after he had put to Death the King of <hi>England:</hi> And as she after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards did with the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and the present <hi>Grand Seignor,</hi> thô they both dethron'd their Brothers. Those Princes, in a word, had been lookt upon as you look upon <hi>Hugh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet;</hi> and all <hi>Europe</hi> would have the same Veneration for you, were you in possession of the Throne, after you had depos'd a Prince, who is esteem'd the Plague and Scourge of Mankind, as it was said of <hi>Attila.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Either you must say, Sir, that all the Deposed Kings which I have reckoned up, was deposed unjustly, and by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence that <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> usurp'd the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> which you will be very wary how you acknowledge, for it is too much your own concern; or else you must grant that a Prince may be sometimes deposed, when there is a lawful Occasion. I have shewed you already, that it is for the Preservation of <hi>France;</hi> that it is to keep the Crown
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35027:48"/> upon your own Head; and that it is for the salvation of the King's Soul. Are not these Arguments sufficiently prevalent? But I will go farther; I will prove that never any Prince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd to be pull'd by Head and Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from his Throne, as <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="discourse">
               <head>The Third Discourse.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THere are some Politicians who maintain, That King's are above the Law; that as they may disannul the Laws, so they may violate them at their pleasure, without any fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing call'd to an Account for so doing. In a word, that their Soveraignty and their Power is nothing else but a <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Impunity.</hi> So that according to this Maxim, a King can never injure his Subjects, let him use them never so barbarously; and that Subjects are always unjust, if they take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35027:49"/> their King; nay, if they so much as murmur at their Oppression.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David,</hi> according to these Morals, might lye with <hi>Bathsheba,</hi> and never fear being call'd to an account, and send her Husband to be slaughter'd, and the People never take it in dudgeon. These are the Prerogatives of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, with which the People have nothing to do. They also farther ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, That when the holy Prophet did Penance for his two Crimes of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and Homicide, that he never ask'd Pardon, either of <hi>Bathsheba</hi> or <hi>Uriah,</hi> nor of his People, but acknowledges only that he had sin'd against God, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee only have I sinned.</hi> They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend also that St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> St. <hi>Ambrose,</hi> and some other Fathers of the Church are of their Opinion. But I am not bound to believe 'em for all that; the Fathers are not infallible Authors; a man might make a long Catalogue of the Errors of those Holy Doctors; and let the Fathers say what they please, 'tis not the Church that speaks.</p>
               <p>If I would turn Divine, I could un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold to you in what sense <hi>David</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses himself after that manner. I
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35027:49"/> could inform you that the Holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet was well satisfied that he had sin'd against <hi>Bathsheba,</hi> in causing her to commit Adultery, one of the foulest Crimes with which a Woman can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file herself; that he had sin'd against <hi>Uriah,</hi> by having dishonoured him in ravishing away his Wife, and afterwards causing him to be murder'd. Lastly, that he had sin'd against his People, whom he had scandalized by his own example. But that he had all this while more heinously offended God by transgressing his Holy Law; having thereby given an occasion to the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcised Nations to blaspheme his Divinity: and in regard that God was without question, more considerable, than either <hi>Bathsheba</hi> or <hi>Uriah,</hi> or his People, he could not but express him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to God as he did, <hi>Against Thee on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have I sinned:</hi> to shew by that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, that it was God with whom he was principally concern'd; and that it was of him that he was chiefly to beg Pardon; and that it was from him alone that he could obtain it, since he alone could only forgive him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store Peace to his Soul, and Tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his Conscience.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:35027:50"/>
               <p>I could tell you moreover, that men may in some measure make amends for Transgressions committed against their Neighbour, but not for Offences committed against their Creator. If one man have <hi>committed an offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst another, a Reconciliation may be made; but if a man have sinned against God, who shall be his Judge?</hi> So that <hi>David</hi> had great reason to say, He had sinned against God only.</p>
               <p>I might say in the third place, That tho' the Prophet was willing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve that tho' he were absolv'd by men; that tho' his People had forgiven him; that tho' no body could reproach him for the Murder and Adultery which he had committed; that tho' to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, and allay his Grief, his Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers might endeavour to excuse his Crimes, nevertheless that he did not believe himself to be really Absolved, unless God himself pardoned him, and therefore it was that he addresses him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self only to him.</p>
               <p>Lastly, I might say, with several of the ancient Writers, that tho' that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had offended men, nevertheless he lookt upon himself as not having other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35027:50"/> offended them, then as God was the only Witness of his Crimes. For, Sir, you must not think that <hi>David</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd <hi>Uriah</hi>'s Wife in the sight of all the People. A wise Prince may some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times forget him, but he always takes care of being publickly observed. He knows that the Miscarriages of a Prince are like the Ecclipses of the Sun; that they come to the knowledge of all the World, and therefore he hides himself in a Cloud, when he gives himself o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to his pleasure; we must not judge of the Conduct of a King of <hi>Judah</hi> by that of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV.</p>
               <p>But I need not so many Arguments. I am perswaded, Sir, that this same Maxim, that gives so much liberty to King's, without the fear of Controul, cannot but offend you; and indeed, it is your Interest to be offended at it. For otherwise the <hi>Bourbons</hi> would be the greatest Usurpers in Nature. For that then it would be true that the People of <hi>France</hi> had no lawful Authority to exclude the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> from the Succession, how undeserving soever he might be.</p>
               <p>We must allow that the greatest Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liticians
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35027:51"/> are not always to be followed; their Politicks are often Politicks of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest. Their principal Aim is to court those Princes from whom they expect Rewards. On the other side, Princes are willing enough to be flattered; yet there is a Law that flows from Nature, which they cannot violate without loosing the Quality of a King: and this Law is the Safety of the People. Kings are their Fathers and their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, as the Ancients call them. And at the very same moment that they cease to be Fathers, or become inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being so, the People ought to Depose them, and elect others in their rooms. A Tyrant, a Mad-man, a weak and simple Prince, are no way fit to govern a Kingdom. If <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. be guilty of any one of these De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, you must acknowledge, Sir, that he ought to be deprived of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Now that he is guilty of them altogether, is no difficult thing to prove.</p>
               <p>For as to the first Head, Sir, there needs no more but to take a view of his whole Life ever since his Minority. For never any Prince exercised a more
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35027:51"/> tyrannick Power than he has done. His miraculous and unexpected Birth gave occasion to <hi>France</hi> to conceive that Heaven, favourable to her prayers and wishes, had sent her a Restorer. But she has had the misfortune to find, that if Heaven gave her a King, it was in its Anger. The <hi>French</hi> (or <hi>Franks</hi>) have but little cause to flatter themselves with bearing a Name that denotes their being a free people, when they are such slaves, as we see them to be, under the Reign of their King <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. For what rank or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men is there in the Kingdom, that can brag of any priviledges? No, no, <hi>France</hi> is truly in Chains.</p>
               <p>I will not speak of the Abolishing of the <hi>States General,</hi> in which Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies our People had a Right to Depose and Elect their Kings; to appoint them Regents and Tutors; to nominate and recommend to the highest Trusts in the Kingdom; to enact Levies and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of Taxes; to make Laws, and redress all Abuses that were crept into the Government. This was a Liberty which was wrested from them b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi> the XIII. when Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> had
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35027:52"/> the sole Government of that Monarch. For it was the Policy of that Minister to extinguish the very memory of the <hi>States General,</hi> if it were possible, as being the only Obstruction to absolute Royal Authority. And in that he acted only for the support of his own Interest. For I had forgot to tell you, that he aspir'd to the Crown, and caus'd <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII. to be poyson'd with a slowly operating Poyson, if we may belive what some Writers do say.</p>
               <p>However, I do not absolutely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse that King, for having ravish'd this <hi>Liberty</hi> from the People; since it was properly the Master piece of him that reigned under the Reign of his Master, and ruled like a perfect Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Nevertheless, I may truly say in this Case, That the King is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether exempt from Tyranny. For if the Assembling of the <hi>States General</hi> be a Right and Priviledge due to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>France;</hi> how comes it to pass, that being absolute, he would never summon any of these Assemblies? He was oblig'd, as a true King, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd all things into their proper Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35027:52"/> and to have restor'd to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Franchises which had been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surped from them in the preceding Reign. For in short, he that approves the Tyranny, is no less a Tyrant, than he that exercises it.</p>
               <p>I must confess there were substituted in the room of these <hi>General States,</hi> those things which you call <hi>Parliaments.</hi> Which at first indeed had some shadow of the Authority of the former.</p>
               <p>For at their first Institution, they had power to judge the Peers and Grandees of the Kingdom: They gave the Oaths to such as were advanc'd to Places of highest Trust; they had the power to verifie the King's Edicts, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their being in force, unless they were verified by them. In a word, they had power to withstand the Will of the Prince, if his Will were unjust. But now these Courts have nothing of Soveraignty but the Title. The Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that compose them are a sort of Illustrious Slaves, by nothing else di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished by the common sort, but by their Purple. They blindly submit to all that comes from the Court. And if there be any Men of Integrity, that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35027:53"/> stand up at any time in resistance of the Court, for the Liberty of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they are either put out of their Places, or ignominiously sent away to the farther end of some Province, where they are either condemned to Death or perpetual Imprisonment, as Rebels and Refractories.</p>
               <p>Now the Grandees of the Kingdom acknowledge no other than the King, who Judges and Sentences them as he pleases by his Commissioners. They are sworn only by the King to their Allegiance, when they are preferr'd to any considerable Employment. And as for the Verification of the King's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts, that Priviledge was altogether disannull'd in the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. The Verifications at this day are meerly Notifications, as has been well observ'd by a great Enemy of the <hi>French</hi> Tyranny. For all the King's Declarations and Edicts are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Registred in the Parliaments, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give the Subjects notice what is the Will of the Prince. If they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to refuse to Register them, the King sends them a new Command, and they must obey. Neither is it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35027:53"/> permitted them under this King to make any Remonstrances: which was a kind of shadow of Liberty, which, till of late, was never taken from them. But should they now Remonstrate, it would be a Crime that <hi>Lewis</hi> would never forgive them.</p>
               <p>These Soveraign Courts, which were the Ramparts of the People's Freedom, and opposed the King's Decrees, when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound them to be unjust, tremble at the sight of a single Letter under the King's Signet, or an Order of an <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</hi> Nay, the King has so far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd his Despotick Power, that a Parliament dares not put to Death a Criminal, for whom the Court has a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kindness, nor pronounce innocent and honest Man, that is disgusted at Court. We have seen of late, in the Case of the Protestants and their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that Father <hi>la Chaise</hi> made all the Decrees that were given out against them: and those poor People some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times adventured to make it out, that they were no way Guilty of the Crimes that were laid to their Charge. Nevertheless, they were condemned for all that. And when they prov'd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35027:54"/> before their Judges that their Sentences were unjust, and that their Judges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times ingeniously confessed them so to be, yet they as ingeniously ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that they had an Order from above, which they durst not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey; and that it was not in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Parliaments, either to do, or not to do Justice. So that the King has most exactly▪ executed the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals Maxim to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII. That it was a Thing of great Importance to prevent his Officers of Justice from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching upon the Royal Authority: In regard, that if he once gave them the Rains, he would never afterwards be able to restrain them within the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of their Duty.</p>
               <p>What are the Estates that assemble every year in certain Provinces? They consist of Bishops, Lords, and the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and Sheriffs of the most considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cities, who are entirely at the King's Devotion; and dare not stand up for the Rights and Priviledges of the People, for fear of being turned out, and debarr'd for ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into any of those Grand Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies. There they formerly were wont
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35027:54"/> to debate, whether they should make a Present to the King, or no; and their Suffrages were free, to vote according to the Dictates of their own Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. When the Thing was concluded, 'twas necessary the King should be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and they agreed upon a Sum, which was call'd a <hi>Free Gift,</hi> because they were at liberty to grant, or not to grant it. Sometimes they were whole Weeks together before they could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree upon the Sum, which at length was ascertained; and if the People were not overcharged, yet the King was to rest satisfied. Now the Face of things is quite altered. The <hi>Free Gift</hi> is a <hi>forc'd Gift.</hi> The King demands what he pleases, and tho' the Sums be never so excessive, they must be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. For who would willingly be banish'd, or incur the disfavour of a Prince, who will not be contradicted, and punishes those sorts of Crimes, as if they were Treasons or Conspiracies against his Person. If the Bishops were now what they were in the times of the Apostles, they would laugh at the Court, and side with their Sheep that consided in them. But these Shepherds
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35027:55"/> are too Politick to run the <hi>Risco</hi> of loosing their Rents: They are under the King's yoke, and they are always the chief Supports of Tyranny.</p>
               <p>The People in general are so over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loaden with Taxes over all the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Kingdom, they are so poor, so miserable, that the Condition to which they are reduced is the subject of all Foreigners Pity. They compare those afflicted People to the Subjects of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Princes, and wonder they do not attempt to set themselves at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. In a word, they are overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Taxes, loaden with an infinite number of Imposts; they are made to pay <hi>Free Gifts,</hi> and such intollerable Tolls, that these Oppressions of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves were enough to reduce them to utter Beggary. But this is not all; they make them labour without any Salary in the publick Works, they force them to the Wars against their wills; they set them to Guard the Frontiers, and quarter the Souldiers upon them in the <hi>Winter</hi> to compleat their Ruin.</p>
               <p>I know well that the Politicians agree, that if the People lived at their ease, it would be impossible to keep
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35027:55"/> them within the bounds of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. They agree, that if they should not be laden with Taxes and Subsidies, they would by little and little lose the remembrance of their Condition, and think of nothing but withdrawing their Obedience from their Prince. And I know that some Princes have lost their Dominions for not having Forces sufficient in Pay, to preserve themselves, for fear of overcharging the People; and that several Subjects have become the Slaves of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for desiring too much Liberty under their Lawful Soveraign. So that the People are to be compared to Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-Horses, which being accustomed to Burthens, are injur'd more by long Repose than by continual Travel; and yet they are not to be over-loaded, but their Burthens must be proportionable to their strength. There ought to be a <hi>Medium</hi> observed, and a stop to be made at such a Point, beyond which it would be a great piece of Injustice to pass, and no less to the prejudice of the Peoples Interest. But this is not the King's Maxim; his Maxim is, to keep the People poor, and to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35027:56"/> he has so impoverished his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that they are all Beggars.</p>
               <p>There is no Kingdom in the World wherein there are so many great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as in <hi>France:</hi> And the greatest part of these Villages enjoy'd an infinite number of Priviledges, which equall'd them to the Free Imperial Cities of <hi>Germany.</hi> They had their Revenues which the King could not touch. They were exempt from Taxes of all sorts of Imposts, except such as they impos'd upon themselves when Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity, when the welfare of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom required it. And lastly, they were the Refuge of the People when they were Oppress'd. But these Cities have lost all their Priviledges. The King has seiz'd upon the greatest part of their Revenues. If he exempts them from Tolls, he makes them pay such excessive Subsidies, that they sink under the Burthen. And he has so bridled them with Forts and Citadels, that there is now no longer any shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter against Tyranny, only when the poor People are under Persecution, they must take the sad choice of voluntary
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:35027:56"/> Banishment, and seeking for Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Foreign Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>How are they us'd that have the Administration of the Grand Affairs? They are advanced to be depress'd. And thô that generally they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich'd in their Employments by the Gratifications which they receive from the King, in consideration of their good Services, yet many times they are Accused for having robb'd the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer: And whether it be true or false, their Estates are presently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscated, and their Persons rendred as miserable, as they were opulent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>I know very well, there are some Officers of the <hi>Finances,</hi> that grow Rich to the prejudice of Orphans and Widows, and to the prejudice of the King himself: And I grant, Sir, that when they are Legally convicted, they are treated like Leeches, which they rub with Salt to make them vomit back all the blood which they have suckt, or Spunges that are squeez'd, to return the Juyce which they have drain'd up. But the King makes no Distinction. To be rich is sufficient to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35027:57"/> be a Criminal; or to be so thought at Court, is a Crime not to be pardoned.</p>
               <p>There must be a Restitution of what they have got, and sometimes of what they never had; and so they must end their days, either in Exile, or in a <hi>Dungeon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be said, and that truly too, that the King has despoil'd, and every day does despoyle an infinite number of honest People, when done him those Services which he ought never to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, tho' perhaps he might find some defect in the Conduct of his Ministers. But one of the principal Characters of a <hi>Tyrant</hi> is Ingratitude. And it may be said of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. what is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually said of Fortune, That many times she takes from her Minions the Favors which she had before in plenty bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them.</p>
               <p>I could produce many Examples upon this Subject, but I shall only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that of Monsieur <hi>Fouquet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This same Superintendant of the Finances had a large and generous Soul, and had he been of any other Profession than that of the Long Robe, his noble Qualities would have
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35027:57"/> been more visible to the World. But Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> had conceiv'd an Aversion against him, for that being Advocate-General of the Parliament, he could not endure to hear that Body, of which he had the Honour to be one of the principal Members, evil spoken of.</p>
               <p>He had told him however, that there were in the Parliament, Persons that he could wish were not there. But this satisfaction being not large enough for an <hi>Italian</hi> that will resent a small Occasion as long as he lives, therefore the Cardinal, who was very effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and durst not shew his disgust, in his life time, upon his Death-bed told the King, that such a Person liv'd upon the waste of his Treasure, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated them also to his own Use; that his Houses exceeded most of the King's Palaces, for beauty of Structure, and magnificence of the Furniture: That he gave Pensions to several per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons at Court, which was a shrew'd sign that he knew himself Guilty; that he fortified <hi>Belle Isle,</hi> a place which he had purchas'd from the House of <hi>Gondy,</hi> a place adjoyning to the Territories of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35027:58"/> the <hi>English,</hi> with whom he was afraid he held a Correspondence. That the only way to pluck up these Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences by the Root, was to secure so dangerous a Person: However, that the King should be careful what he did, while he was Advocate-General, for that then the Parliament would be his Judges, and without doubt acquit him; and that he should therefore so order his business, that the Thing should be put in Execution before he had the least suspicion of it.</p>
               <p>Thus went Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> into the other World, a true <hi>Italian</hi> to his last gasp: for a little before he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, he had embrac'd Monsieur <hi>Fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet,</hi> as one of his best Friends: he had numbred up to him a thousand Kindnesses, which the Superintendant had done him, in the time of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Wars, and thank'd him particularly for the Fifty thousand Crowns which he sent him, at the time he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fly to <hi>Liege.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However the King took no great heed of what the Cardinal told him. For indeed, what a likely thing it was Monsieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> should hold private
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35027:58"/> Correspondencies with the <hi>English,</hi> who were then in a strict Friendship with <hi>France,</hi> and that he should think of betraying his Country, who was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to one of the highest Places of Profit, to which one of the Long Robe could aspire.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless the King was convinc'd that Monsieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> was very rich, and for that reason he determin'd his destruction, to the end he might seize upon his Estate. He kept this as a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret for some time; and when he declar'd his mind, 'twas only to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Tellier,</hi> whose Fidelity was well known to him, and to Monsieur <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> whom the <hi>Cardinal</hi> upon his Death-bed had recommended to him for his Chief Minister.</p>
               <p>These two Men, who were the Chief Ministers of the King's Injustice, fail'd not to confirm him in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign; but withal advis'd him, not to do any thing, till he had put Monsieur <hi>Fouquet,</hi> out of his place of <hi>Advocate General,</hi> or force him to lay it down.</p>
               <p>Wanting therefore a pretence to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage Monsieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> to answer their Desires, <hi>Colbert</hi> insinuates into his
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35027:59"/> head, that having such a multiplicity of Business at the Council, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed lay all upon his shoulders, since the death of the Cardinal, he would do well to quit his Affairs in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which it was impossible for him to look after as he ought to do. And to lull him the more easily a-sleep, the King lookt upon him with a more Gracious Aspect than ever he had done before. So that Monsieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the Snare, saught for a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant for his Employment, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the best that was in the Parliament, was contended for by all that had mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney enough to purchase it: and among the rest, Monsieur <hi>de Foubet</hi> offer'd six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred thousand Livers. But Monsieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> chose rather to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render it to Monsieur <hi>de Harlay,</hi> who was one of his Friends, thô he gave him Two hundred thousand Franks less.</p>
               <p>Thus he had no sooner laid down his Employment, but the King caus'd him to be arrested. And because they were afraid least he should find a way to justifie himself, in regard the Crimes alledg'd against him were only Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35027:59"/> they were not only conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with hiring false Witnesses to swear dreadful things against him, but they took away from him all his Papers that could any way have serv'd him to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie his Innocency. Nor was this all, for the King, who was resolv'd to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine him at any rate, employ'd <hi>Colbert,</hi> to pick and cull out of all the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, such Judges as he thought were most devoted to his Service, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Monsieur <hi>Fouquets</hi> Charge, and to Judge him. To which purpose they were promised Rewards, and the King thought himself so Cocksure of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Fouquet</hi>'s Death, that he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready commanded his Horse-Guard to be ready to attend him to <hi>Chartres.</hi> A Journey which he had premeditated, not out of Devotion, but to avoid the Importunities with which he foresaw he should be troubled in the behalf of that unfortunate Minister. For tho' Monsieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> were of no extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary or illustrious Descent, he had married one of his Daughters to the eldest Son of the Count of <hi>Charost,</hi> and the King was afraid of that Ladies throwing herself at his Feet.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:35027:60"/>
               <p>To be short, the Commissioners met and examined the business. But while the King, who was booted and spurr'd, and ready to take Horse, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected they should bring him News of the Prisoners being condemn'd, word was brought him, That the Judges had been more merciful. 'Tis true, there were some that would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd him to the Scaffold, according to the King's Orders; but others op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd so great a piece of Injustice, and they prevail'd.</p>
               <p>Among the rest, one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners who was a Counsellor in the Parliament of <hi>Aix,</hi> perceiving the greatest part of the Judges no way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to do Monsieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> Justice, stood up and told them: He was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly surpriz'd, that there should be Men so much prejudiced in the Chamber, as to condemn a Man to Death, without examining before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, whether their Sentence were just or no. He shew'd them the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the Proofs to convince the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner of Treason. That if his Papers had not been taken from him by his Enemies, he might have found a way
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:35027:60"/> perhaps to have justified himself, as to that point. However it was certain, that he had clear'd himself of the Charge of Bribery and Extortion, which they pretended he was guilty of: That he had made appear the Condition of his Estate when he first entred into the Ministry; what he had with his Wife, which was above a Million; what Pensions had been bestow'd on him, and what other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages he had had to get Money: Notwithstanding all which, he had not only spent all, but was above two Millions in debt. So that they could not make him a Criminal because of his great Expences, since he had an Estate to spend without doing any wrong to his Majesty; and besides, that it appear'd, that he was ruin'd in his Majesties Service.</p>
               <p>The greatest part of the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners wonder'd not so much at the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and boldness which the Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor us'd in his Speech, but that he durst oppose the King's pleasure, since he knew how eagerly he sought the Superintendant's Death. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, the good Example of one honest
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35027:61"/> Man wrought such a Change in the Chamber, that they who spoke after the <hi>Counseller,</hi> agreed with him in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and they that were for putting <hi>Fouquet</hi> to Death before, then alter'd theirs. Nevertheless, because it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that Monsieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> had fortified <hi>Belle Isle</hi> of his own Head, without leave from the King, he was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to perpetual Banishment.</p>
               <p>But the King, who was extreamly surpriz'd at this unexpected Sentence, believing that if he should get out of his reach, he would write in his own Justification, changed the Sentence of Banishment into perpetual Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was worse than Death it self. First therefore he was thrown into the Dungeon of <hi>Vincennes,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that carried to <hi>Pigneroll,</hi> where he lay seventeen years, the most misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Men. But as terrible as that Prison was, it prov'd a happy Prison to him: For there he had leisure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him of his sins, which he had not at Court, which was at that time gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over to all manner of Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Great-men still believing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves oblig'd to imitate their Prince,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35027:61"/> tho' never so dissolute and luxurious.</p>
               <q>Regis ad exemplum totus componitur Orbis.</q>
               <p>In truth, he had liv'd in the Prison like a real Penitent: he made the place of his Punishment a House of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Prayer: There he learnt to draw off his Soul from the World; and thinking upon nothing in that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable place but upon Eternity, he lookt upon his past Prosperity as a great Obstacle to his Salvation, so that he would not have exchanged his Prison for all the Kingdoms in the World.</p>
               <p>I thought fit, Sir, to let you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand a Story, of which I was assured you were altogether ignorant. For I have always heard you talking of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Fouquet,</hi> as of a Minister that had conspired against his Majesty, and had enrich'd himself by robbing the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Believe me, Sir, his pretended Riches were his Misfortune, and had like to have brought him to an Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Death. He was a Man of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Honour, and had not the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment been Tyrannical, they would have erected Statues to his Memory, he
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35027:62"/> had so well merited of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, to speak in the Language of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You will say perhaps, Sir, That Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> was no more than one of the Long Robe, and that the rest that were serv'd after the same manner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> were only under Receivers, and Toll-gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: Fellows not thought worth the hanging, as being of mean and obscure Birth. In a word, that those Officers, being a sort of necessary Evils, and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the People, it is no great matter what becomes of 'em; and that it is good policy sometimes to fetch them down from the top of the Wheel whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fortune has raised them, to make advantage of their ill-got Wealth.</p>
               <p>But what, Sir, will you conclude from hence? Let an Excise-man or a Toll-gather be never so mean, he ought to be punish'd when he is Guilty, and has devour'd the People. But let his Birth be never so obscure, if he have dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd his Duty like an honest Man, is an abominable piece of Tyranny to rob him of his Estate. 'Tis the Law of Nature, that every man ought to enjoy
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:35027:62"/> his own; and 'tis a sin to violate this Law.</p>
               <p>But we have done with Monsieur▪ <hi>Fouquet,</hi> and the Officers of the Revenue. I do not find but they who are much higher in degree, are better or more kindly used than those ordinary sort of people. The same Tyranny reaches the very Princes of the Blood. For not to say any thing of that <hi>Hero</hi> the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> whom the King confin'd to <hi>Chantilly,</hi> because he would not give him an Employment in his Army; such Policies admitting Excuses for Reasons which all the World knows not; how does the King use several other Princes that never gave him any occasion of distrust. He suffers them to live a lazy and private Life: he would never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to appear upon any occasion wherein they might signalize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. If they are desirous to try their Courages, they must be forc'd to travel into <hi>Hungary,</hi> whither his Majesty will or no. Which prov'd fatal to the Prince of <hi>Conty,</hi> who was poison'd at his Return as most People believ'd. He has depriv'd them, and excluded them from Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that were almost Hereditary to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:35027:63"/> their Families, to bestow them upon Bastards. How do they use both you and Madam the <hi>Dauphiness</hi> your illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious Spouse? You know it well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, there is no need of telling you. And it may give credit to what is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly talk'd abroad, Madam the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiness</hi> has not long to live. The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, which were formerly the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Strength of the Kingdom, are now under a diminution that renders them the Scorn of the Earth. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, that they are reduc'd to so small a number, they are reduced to such an extream Poverty, that 'tis impossible they should long subsist.</p>
               <p>There are some Provinces where the Gentlemen go to Plough and Cart; and there are others who are forc'd to marry below themselves, to prevent their own starving in their Castles, or the being oblig'd to meaner Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scensions. 'Tis true, there are some Gentlemen whom their riotous Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have impoverish'd; but generally 'tis the Tyrannical Government, and Oppression of the People, that causes these Disorders, to the reproach of <hi>France.</hi> Formerly the Nobility enjoy'd
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:35027:63"/> several Priviledges, and were exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Taxes, Subsidies, and Imposts. Now 'tis, All Fellows at Foot-ball, as to that point. A Lord pays the same Duties as the meanest Vassal, and an Intendant of a Province, who sometimes happens to be one of the Drags of the People, will use them with the highest degree of Pride and Contempt. The Title of Noble is but a word, and there are only some few new Gentlemen that derive their Original from the Publick Revenue, that dare aspire to Military Employments, because they have wherewithal to purchase them. An ancient Nobleman, who shall have signaliz'd himself a thousand times by his Courage and Gallantry, who has receiv'd several Wounds, and spent his Patrimony in the Service, shall dye a Lieutenant, or a Captain of Foot or Dragoons, while the Son of a Subsidy-Gatherer shall ride at the Head of a Regiment, or some other considerable Employment. What respect is there show'd to the Gentry? No, no more then for the Common Rabble. If they have happen'd at any time to have wrong'd their Vassals, there is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:35027:64"/> Session appointed by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, called the <hi>Grands-Jours,</hi> to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stize them; and these dreadful Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are always fatal to some conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Family or other. And you, Sir, have seen some Persons of eminent Degree, who have lost their Heads upon Scaffolds for being accus'd, in i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of the King, to set up for petty Tyrants in their Inheritances.</p>
               <p>What more crying piece of Injustice was there, than the Enquiry after <hi>False Nobles?</hi> How many real Gentlemen were there, who because they could not produce their Pedigrees, which they might loose by a thousand Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, were constrained to renounce their Nobility, and pay a hundred and thirteen <hi>Livres,</hi> which was their forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>I know that all that call themselves Noblemen, are not so; and that the most part of those that assume this Title, ground it upon their Merit: and what can be more unjust, than to wrest their honour out of their hands? Is not that true Nobility, Sir, that is atchieved by Feats of Arms? Their Courage has acquir'd what their Birth refus'd them.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35027:64"/> Why should they be depriv'd of an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which they have merited by their Services? Stay till they have render'd themselves unworthy, and then let them be degraded. But the King would fain tyrannize over all the World. And this blind Passion reigns so strongly in him, that are most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for his Service, and who ought to be regarded as the support of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Formerly the Officers and Souldiers enriched themselves by being in the Army, or at least they could subsist in a comfortable manner: A younger Brother, who was of a reduc'd Family, had Bread to eat as long as he liv'd, if he could but get a Command, either by his own Merit, or the assistance of his Friends: It was the same thing with the Common Souldier. But in this Man's Reign, there is no more of that. They that have any Estate, spend it in his Majesties Service. If the Souldiers will live, they put their Hosts to ransome their Goods. And which is more tyrannical, the Officers and Souldiers are forc'd to commit such infamous Actions, and so unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:35027:65"/> Gentlemen Souldiers, that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ages will hardly believe, that People wearing Swords by their sides, should have such dastardly Souls, as not to shake off the Yoke of a Prince that never employs them, for whole Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigns together, but to do the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Hangmen, Robbers and House burners.</p>
               <p>I should but give you too much trouble, Sir, to make a long Recital of these things. The King spares no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. He has exercis'd his Tyranny o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Protestants, who were his most faithful Subjects, and set the Crown upon his Head, as they did upon the Heads of <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. and <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII. He has recall'd their Edicts, thô he solemnly swore at his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to observe and maintain them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable. And usurping the Rights of God himself, who is the sole Lord of Hearts and Consciences, and who in that respect, parts with his Honour to no Mortal. He has oblig'd them by force to embrace a Religion which they believe to be false and idolatrous; constraining them by that means to prophane our most Sacred Mysteries,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:35027:65"/> by how much the more he causes them to condemn and renounce them. For he that makes Profession of a Religion against his Conscience, commits the most horrid of all Crimes, thô the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which he profest were sincerely the only True Religion: <hi>For what is not of Faith, is sin:</hi> That is, whatever is not done according to Conscience is an offence against God.</p>
               <p>He has exercis'd his Tyranny over the most holy Party of the Church o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver those Disciples of St. <hi>Austin,</hi> who live such pious and exemplary lives. For those holy Fathers grounding their Doctrine upon the words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, <hi>It is better to obey God than men:</hi> would not subscribe to a <hi>Formulary,</hi> which was a kind of Oath, which they could not in Conscience take. He has therefore despoil'd them of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, has exil'd them, or shut them up in dark Prisons, where they starve to Death, or suffer the Extremities of Miseries. He has no regard for the most pious Virgins, under pretence that they were <hi>Jansenists,</hi> and refus'd to deny, that the Grace of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> was sufficient of itself.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:35027:66"/>
               <p>This Prince, a Rebel to the <hi>Church,</hi> has extended a Supreme Power, as well over the Bishops, as over all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Houses. You know the business of the <hi>Regale,</hi> (or Patronage of Bishops) and the Nuns of <hi>Santa Clara,</hi> common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Urbanists.</hi> And to carry his Tyranny to the highest degree, he has quarrell'd with the Vicar of Christ, whom we ought to look upon as a God upon Earth. Why do ye not Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate him, Holy Father? Why do you not strike him with the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of your Anathema's? Why do you not dart upon his Head all the Thunder of the <hi>Vatican?</hi> You are but the Image of a Pope, in respect of the <hi>Gallican Church. Lewis</hi> the Great, the Most Christian King makes you inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to Councils, and declares you sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Errour, thô you ought to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, if you are St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor, and that the Catholick Church be the Spouse of Jesus Christ. And yet there needs no more, then for your Children to have recourse to you, to incur the Indignation of this Prince, and to be dealt withal in the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as Hereticks.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:35027:66"/>
               <p>In a word, Sir, if the Bishops of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers,</hi> and <hi>D' Alet</hi> were expos'd to the extremity of Persecution, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they address'd themselves to the <hi>Holy See,</hi> to the end the Pope might make use of his Authority to maintain the Priviledges of the Church. And for the same reason it was, that he so barbarously us'd the Congregation of <hi>Nuns,</hi> I mean the <hi>Nuns</hi> of the <hi>Enfance,</hi> or <hi>Infancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Society of <hi>Nuns,</hi> call'd, The <hi>Nuns of the Infancy of Jesus Christ,</hi> was instituted at <hi>Tholouse,</hi> in the Year 1662, by the Authority of <hi>M. de Marca,</hi> Arch-bishop of that place, and under the Government of M. <hi>de Ciron,</hi> Canon and Chancellor of that Church and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversity; by whose Advice Madam <hi>de Mondonville,</hi> a Widow of great Piety became the Foundress of the Society, and for the Maintenance of it, left them the best part of her Estate: The Employment of these Nuns was to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducate young Girles in the knowledge of the Duties to which they were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd by their Baptism; and in other Vertuous Exercises: They were also to teach them to Read and Write, and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:35027:67"/> work with their Needles. This Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution which could not but be lookt upon as a thing very praise worthy, was approv'd by the whole Church, and confirm'd by a Bull of <hi>Alexander</hi> the VII. But all this signified nothing. For because the King had not institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Order, he resolv'd to ruin it: and Madam <hi>Mondonville,</hi> because she address'd herself to the <hi>Holy See,</hi> was sent to a Prison, where she still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lastly,</hi> Sir, the King does not only exercise his Tyranny with less rigour over those without, than over his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Subjects. 'Tis the Custom of Conquerors to have some regard for the People whom they have newly conquer'd. And indeed, thô it were no piece of Justice to make them sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction by some kind of Lenity, for the Ravage committed upon their Lands before they could be subdu'd, yet there is something of Policy that requires it. Nevertheless, both <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne, Flanders, Franche Contè,</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satia</hi> have experienced the contrary. Those Countries groan under their Bondage, and are so weary of their
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:35027:67"/> Yoke, that they only wait the happy Moment of their Delivery, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation to the Dominion of their Lawful Soveraigns.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="discourse">
               <head>The Fourth Discourse.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have proved by Actions, which are onely too true, that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>France</hi> is wholly tyrannical, whether in respect of Spirituals or Temporals. Of which I could bring farther proofs of those which I have brought already, were not these un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily more than sufficient.</p>
               <p>But this is not all, Sir; it remains that I prove to you, that the Tyranny which he exercises in this Kingdom, is the most cruel that ever was heard of. In a word, I am now to prove, That the King is a Mad-man of a Tyrant; and I am sure you must yield to what I say.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:35027:68"/>
               <p>What could I not tell you, if I would make a recital of all those unheard of Hostilities which he has committed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this last War, particularly in the Principality of <hi>Orange</hi> and <hi>Germany.</hi> What a dreadful <hi>Landskip</hi> could I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to your eyes, if I should speak of the Persecution of the <hi>Jansenists;</hi> more especially if I would enlarge upon the Torment, unknown to <hi>Phalaris</hi> or <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siris,</hi> which he has invented to punish those that run from his Colours? I could shew you whole Cities laid in Ashes; People expos'd to the rage and fury of the Souldiers; Women and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins ravish'd; old Men and tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants expiring in the flames; Prisons fill'd with Priests, and infinite numbers of poor Wretches in Cains, some with their Noses, some with their Ears cut off, after they had exposed their Lives a thousand times for the most ingrateful of Princes.</p>
               <p>This last Prospect, I am sure, strikes you with horror: For certainly, Sir, a more dismal Prospect cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Thus to disfigure the Image of God! to make of a Man a hideous Monster! to dismember a Christian,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:35027:68"/> and it may be one design'd for Heaven! 'Tis an Accumulation of madness, rage, and barbarity altogether.</p>
               <p>What shall I say after all this? I will begin with the Protestant. What wrong had those People done the King? Had they not been always faithful to him? That was not their Crime, Sir; for we must acknowledge to the shame of our Religion, that while the greatest part of the Catholicks sided with the Princes in the last Civil Wars, that stood al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways firm to the King: and it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them that the King was beholding for his Crown. That which made them Criminals was, that they would not turn Catholicks, and that they would not yield him Obedience by changing their Religion. And yet they did all they could to let him understand that they should act against their Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if they should abandon their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, and the Doctrines of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; nevertheless, the King would have it so. And because they refus'd to obey his Orders, tho' with all the respect imaginable, his Fury kindled against them. There was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Age nor Sex, neither Merit nor
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35027:69"/> Quality, that was spared at that time. He let loose his <hi>Dragoons</hi> upon them. He set up Villains and Robbers to be their Converters; and like another <hi>Mahomet,</hi> he made use of Fire and Sword to force them to receive his Doctrine.</p>
               <p>With what Colours shall I draw the hideous Picture of these abominable Conversions, at which the <hi>Holy See</hi> trembles to this day, and which have drawn so many tears from the eyes of all real <hi>Catholicks?</hi> So soon as this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Prince understood that his Protestant Subjects had return'd a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Answer, That they would dye in their Religion, because they believ'd it to be the Truth; and that bating on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this point, they would sacrifice their Lives for his Honour; he gave order to his Converters to thunder into all the Provinces that abounded with the <hi>Religionaries,</hi> and to make use of all means to force their Return to the Church. He let them know, that whatever it cost him, he would have his Pleasure put in Execution, and save them harmless from all the Barbarities whatever they committed.</p>
               <p>There needed not half so much, Sir,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:35027:69"/> to animate a Company of Brutes, that never signalized themselves for many years, but by their treacheries and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Actions. They forthwith hast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to execute the barbarous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of their Cruel Monarch; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was there any sort of Inhumanity which those Infernal Legions forgot to put in practise. I might swell whole Volumes with the Oppressions and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olences of these leud <hi>Converters,</hi> and the strange and unheard of Torments which they invented to preach up the King's Religion.</p>
               <p>They no sooner entred into any Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but they seiz'd upon the Gates and all the Avenues, while others beat the Streets to stop the Fugitives, and bring them back to their Houses, on purpose to force them, in spite of their Teeths, to hear the Sermons of these abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Apostles.</p>
               <p>They were quarter'd at discretion by order of the Intendants of the Province, and sometimes of the Bishops them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, to the shame of the Episcopal Dignity. And they no sooner entred into any House, but they fill it with most horrible Cries, accompanied with
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35027:70"/> a thousand Blasphemies. You would have said, Sir, that they were so many Devils let loose, and that they were broke out of Hell to make War upon Mankind. Neither Tears nor Submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions would move them. They hang'd both Men and Women by the feet, or hair of their Heads upon the planks of the Cieling, or Hooks in the Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys. They plung'd them into Wells, or into Sloughs full of mud and filth. They half roasted them, and basted their naked Limbs with melted Grease. They thrust red hot Coals into the Palms of their Hands, then closed them by force. They poured Wine into their Bodies with Funnels. They blew them up with Bellows till their Bellies burst. They tore the Hair from their Chins and Heads, and their Nails from their Fingers and Toes. They stript them naked, and after they had offered them a thousand Indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they larded them with Pins from Head to foot. They pinkt and gash'd their Skins with Pen-knives, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with red hot Pincers, nip'd the Flesh from their Arms, or else took them by the Noses, and so led them from room to room.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:35027:70"/>
               <p>Modesty will not permit to tell the Ignominies that Women and Virgins were constrained to undergo. I shall only say that they ravished se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral, and some in the Presence of their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Fathers, whom they had tyed to the Bed-posts.</p>
               <p>I should never have done, should I relate the various sorts of Torments which those Infernal <hi>Missionaries</hi> invented to plant the Catholick Faith in the Hearts of the King's Subjects. They did those things which perhaps the Devils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves would not have thought of. And when they found that those whom they so tormented, endured all, they bethought themselves at length how to make them mad, by hindring them from sleep for whole weeks together. Rich and Poor, Men and Women, Young and Old, Sick and Sound, all without distinction, deeply experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced their Barbarity. While the King and his Confessor laught at their Inhumanities that drew so much Blood, and such showers of Tears from those Religious People.</p>
               <p>I confess, this new way of Conversion was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more prevalent than the most Eloquent Sermons they could have preach'd. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, it could not prevail upon a great number; and then it was that this same <hi>Frantick</hi> Monarch, who would have no Denyals, fill'd all the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Dungeons, Galleys, and the <hi>new World</hi> with infinite Multitudes of these miserable Wretches, who in regard of the good Services they had done him, were worthy of a bett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Reward.</p>
               <p>What was <hi>France</hi> all this while, but a Theater which Strangers beheld with dread and horror? The Hangmen were at work all hours: there was nothing to be seen but <hi>Executions;</hi> and they that dyed Rebels to the King's Orders, were
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:35027:71"/> drag'd along the <hi>Streets,</hi> to be a Spectacle to the People, and then thrown into the <hi>Common Sewers.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Tantum Religio potuit suadare malorum.</q>
               <p>No, Sir, it was not any Zeal for Religion that occasion'd all these Desolations; for Religion ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thirsted after Blood. However, at the same time that the King was thus busie in Converting his own Subjects, he prevented the Emperour from Converting his. For who can be ignorant of his strict Confederacy at that time with the Male-contents in <hi>Hungary,</hi> who are all <hi>Lutherans</hi> or <hi>Calvinists.</hi> But that will more clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you than any thing else, that it was only an Impulse of blind Fury, and hairbrain'd Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, to make himself ador'd as a God, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spir'd him to commit these Barbarities, was the Usage of those poor Nuns of the Infancy, already mentioned.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>de Mondon Ville</hi> the Foundress of that Religious Society, upon the first Rumours that prov'd but too true, that the King had a design to overthrow that pious Institution, was advised to go to <hi>Paris,</hi> and throw herself at the King's Feet. Which Advice she took forthwith, but to no purpose: For the King was always inaccessible and at the same time that she was importunate for Admission, and was in hopes of obtaining it, she was by virtue of a Letter under the Privy Signet, commanded to go to <hi>Coutance.</hi> There was no refusing; she obey'd; and immediately after her Exilement, the Councel by Decree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished the Foundation, and ordered the Nuns of the Infancy to go home to their Parents, or whither else they pleased.</p>
               <p>I know not whether you will find the like in
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:35027:71"/> any History. For a usual piece of Injustice to condemn People in their absence, before they be heard; but for a Lady of Quality, to come above a hundred and fifty Leagues, to throw herself at the King's Feet, and to be so barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously us'd, is that for which there never was yet any President to be found.</p>
               <p>The Arrest, or Decree was made the 12th of <hi>May,</hi> 1686, and fifteen days after was signified at <hi>Tholouse</hi> to Madam <hi>de Mondonville,</hi> thô she were then banish'd to the farther end of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor was this all; for in regard the Tenor of the King's Decree was positive, <hi>That the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles in the Churches of those Nuns should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, that the Altars should be pull'd down, the Ornaments and Holy Ʋtensils carried away, and the Consecrated Places be Prophan'd.</hi> The same day that the Decree was Notified, the Chappel was pull'd down, as if it had been a Mosque, or some notorious Brothel-House.</p>
               <p>Nor did the King stop here. For whereas there was a Clause in the Decree, That all the Nuns of the Infancy might stay in their Nunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries till the end of the Year; yet he sent down an Order to those of <hi>Tholouse,</hi> by which above Forty of the Nuns, who brought nothing to the Society, were commanded to depart imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. To which purpose a Commissary, with a Guard of Souldiers was sent to dispossess them; but the Nuns being inform'd of it, hid themselves so privately, that not above two or three of them were found, who were carried away, after seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Abuses offer'd them.</p>
               <p>As for the rest, some few days after the same Commissary had another Order, to take a Guard of Dragoons and Archers, and go and pull them
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:35027:72"/> out of the House, who found them upon their knees upon the Ruines of their Chappel, implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the assistance of Heaven. Nor could the Tears of those pious Virgins, nor all their Sighs and Sobs, enough to mollifie the Hearts of the most Cruel, prevail with those Miscreants who were sent to hale them from their Religious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidencies. Those Emissaries of the Devil, which the King made use of to Convert the Hereticks, laid their polluted hands, upon the Spouses of Jesus Christ, dragg'd them by the Feet like mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable Victims, beat them, tore them, and talk'd to 'em those broad Obscenities, enough to have made the most impudent of Prostitutes blush.</p>
               <p>Lastly, Sir, some time after the same Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences were exercis'd upon the rest of the Nuns that remain'd. And that which was more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, and cries loudest to Heav'n for Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, was this: That they haul'd two out of the Nunnery that were <hi>Agonisantes,</hi> or in Swoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fits. There was one that swooned away six times in the street, and when all the People cry'd out shame, the Souldiers answer'd, That the King's Orders were express, that the Nuns were obstinate, and the King must be obey'd. I shall say nothing of those other Nunneries of this Institution, in other Cities; their Destiny was the same; I pass by also the Cruelties committed upon the Foundress of the Order, with an infinite number of other mad Actions, with which this King has defil'd his Government. I shall now shew you, Sir, that the King is a weak Prince.</p>
               <p>You may think this hard to be done: because the King has been always accounted a <hi>Great Wit:</hi> But I assure you, Sir, he has little deserved that Title, as his Title of <hi>Most Christian King.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:35027:72"/>
               <p>Should I go about to make a History of the several Mistresses he has had, that have shorten'd the Life of the Queen, that Great and Pious Princess, I could shew you such Weaknesses and Follies that few Men are guilty of. I could shew him to you upon his knees, crying and blubbering sometimes at <hi>La Valiere</hi>'s Feet, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at the side of Madam <hi>de Montespan</hi>'s, or <hi>Madamoselle de Fontanges</hi> Bed, to obtain those Favours which others had obtain'd without any trouble, and of which they told such Tales, that all the Court knew of. I could shew you the Copies of certain Letters, where you might see <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Grand</hi> uttering those little Things, as would grieve your heart to hear them. But pardon him the Imbecillities of his youthful Inclinations. The Women had those Charms, that it is no wonder he should forget himself sometimes. <hi>Hercules</hi> spun for <hi>Omphales</hi>'s sake; and you have read the Amours of Great Men. But what can you say, <hi>Sir,</hi> to his ridiculous Dotage upon Madam <hi>Maintenon:</hi> Let the Lady have Wit, let her have as much as you please; she has not been in a Condition to conquer hearts this long time. Were there no more in it, but only that she was <hi>Scarron</hi>'s Wife, 'twere enough to make all the World stop their Noses at her. Besides, who can be ignorant of her Intrigues, both before, and after her Marriage. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless the King is so weak, that he moans to her the same Turtelisms of Tenderness and Affection, with which he would cocker and feddle a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, the chastest Woman in the World, or a blooming Beauty. He writes to her tender <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let douxs;</hi> cringes to her with a thousand Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions. He lies publickly with her, when his Distempers will permit him; and he brought
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:35027:73"/> so under her Girdle, that he can deny her nothing in the World.</p>
               <p>It may be said, that Madam de <hi>Maintenon,</hi> and Father <hi>La Chaise,</hi> are the absolute Controulers of his Heart. And because you cannot deny this to be true, because you are a Witness of it every day, you must allow it to be the height of folly for a Prince that all his Life-time hath usurp'd the Title of Great, to suffer himself to be govern'd by a Wench and a Priest.</p>
               <p>I could make some Reflections upon a thing which he did so pitiful, especially speaking of <hi>La Chaise,</hi> that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> painted him some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times since, leading <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great by the Nose. But these are Reflections which you are able to make your self. I must stop at Matters of Fact.</p>
               <p>What think you of the Marriages of the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> last deceased; and the Duke of <hi>Enguien,</hi> now Prince of <hi>Condè.</hi> Were ever two such Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples known in a Prince pretending to Wit? It was not enough for him to have liv'd for twenty Years together in a double Adultery; to have depriv'd one of his most faithful Subjects of his Wife; to have enjoy'd her in the face of the Church and his own Queen, but he must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summate his folly, by mixing the Illustrious Blood of the <hi>Bourbon's,</hi> with that of two Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets. I confess, the two Princesses descended from those Adulterous <hi>Coritons,</hi> are Vertuous Ladies. But their Original is so ignominious, that it had become the Wisdom of the King, instead of matching them to two Princes of the Blood, he had never suffer'd them to appear in the World. But Princes like <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, never consult their Reason.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:35027:73"/>
               <p>What Judgment is to be made of a Prince, that after he has exercis'd upon his Subjects, all the most cruel Persecutions that can enter into Man's imagination, suffers himself to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently flatter'd: <hi>That he never made use of any other means than those of Sweetness and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; that he converted the Hereticks without Arms and Force, and far less by the Terror of his Edicts, than by his Exemplary Piety; that the ways through which he caus'd them to pass, were ways strewed with flowers; that he had extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Heresie without noise or effusion of Blood; and that far from suffering Torments, they never so much as heard them mentioned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Judgment which is to be made upon it is this, that there is no Prince in the World so weak and foolish as <hi>Lewis the Great.</hi> And it is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, Sir, that they say no more of him: For what is to be said to an infirm King, to a King that dotes, to a King that is half in his Coffin, but what his Treacher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note n="*" place="margin">The Bishop of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> the Coadjutor <hi>de Rouer,</hi> Father <hi>Maim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> and others.</note> Flatterers tell him in reference to the Persecution of the Protestants in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>But this is nothing yet; here is an Accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Folly. He permits his Statues to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and to be ador'd in the Posture of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sternation: He permits Holy-days to be dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them; and Harangues to be made them, as if they were so many Deities; so that upon the Basis of these Idols, you shall see these In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions in Capital Characters,
<q>TO THE IMMORTAL MAN.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:35027:74"/>
               <p>He suffers himself in publick Themes to be advanced above the Angels, and to be lookt upon as a Proof of our Sublime Mysteries; and that the words once said of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> should be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to him; <hi>My Works are for the King; Who is the King? 'Tis</hi> Lewis the Great the <hi>King of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lastly, He suffers himself to be worshipt like a Deity. You saw this in the Fire-works upon the <hi>Greve,</hi> under the Title of the <hi>Temple of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> which were made to solemnize the Erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the new Statute that was set up in the Court of the Common-Hall of the City. The Inscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was upon the <hi>Frize,</hi> and upon the four Fronts of the Temple, was after the Jesui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Manner, and no less Impious.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The City of <hi>Paris,</hi> Pious, Loyal,</l>
                  <l>Obedient, Devoted by publick Vows</l>
                  <l>To the Divinity and Majesty of</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, the Father of his Country</l>
                  <l>As a Monument of their Duty, Dedicate</l>
                  <l>and Consecrate a Temple.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I could number up a thousand things of this nature; but doubtless here is enough to prove what I have advanc'd, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great has three Characters, which justifie his Deposal; you may consider of them, Sir; it concerns the Safety and Welfare of a Kingdom; it concerns the Preservation of a Crown that belongs to your self.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Damis</hi> in <hi>Philostratus,</hi> wonders to see an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant led by a young Man not above fifteen Years of Age. But I should wonder more, if you should suffer <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. to hold the Reins of Government, after all that I have said
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:35027:74"/> to you. He is a <hi>Phaeton</hi> that ought to be pull'd down from the Chariot of the Sun. He has been a long time unable to Govern. Do you not see, Sir, all the Kingdom in a flame? If you do it not your self, Sir, the People will do it for you; for they are no longer able to endure his Tyranny. If the People will not do it, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners will do it. They have explain'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with their Arms in their hands: they can no longer brook the Madness and Phrensie of a King that Burns, Massacrees, and lays desolate their most beautiful Cities, where-ever his Troops get footing: And if neither his own Subjects, nor his Enemies can do it, the Vengeance of God will do it; for he is a jealous God, and never parts with his Honour to another.</p>
               <p>A King who usurps the Regalities of the God of Hosts, is a thousand times more criminal than a Subject that seizes unjustly upon the Crown of any Prince: for there is no proportion between the God of Heaven, and an earthly King; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Almighty, and a mortal Man. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is some proportion and agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a King and his Subjects. But the King visibly sets himself up in God's Place. He will have Men to be of his Religion; not because his Religion is true, but because it is the Religion which he professes: that is, if he were a <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metam,</hi> or the King of <hi>Siam,</hi> he would require the same thing from his Subjects. But what is more detestable, he permits himself to be ador'd as a God, and prostremation at the Feet of his Statues.</p>
               <p>But know, Sir, that God is no less just at this day, then when he sent <hi>Nebuchodonozer</hi> to graze among the Beasts of the Field, for suffering his Statue to be ador'd; or when he suffered <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:35027:75"/> to be eaten up of Worms, for hearkning to the impious Acclamations of a hair-brain'd Rabble, that after he had made them a harangue, cry'd, This is the Voice of God, and not of Man. <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great was tickl'd with the Lies of his Flatterers, who told him. He was the Son of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> and that Divine Honours ought to be paid him, was poyson'd in the midst of his Triumphs. <hi>Antiochus</hi> the <hi>Illustrious,</hi> who like <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. had got a whim in his head, to have all People profess one Religion, commands all People to forsake the Laws of God, and follow his; but his end was sad and tragical. <hi>Nero, Caligula, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and several others that required to be ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as Gods, came to most fatal Exits, answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Lives they had led. And what can you expect less to befal your Father; he that has priz'd himself upon the Impiety of those Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and never took notice of the defacing the Name of JESUS out of the Frontispiece of the Jesuit's Colledge, to put his own in the room of it<note n="*" place="bottom">The Colledge of <hi>Clermont,</hi> which is at this day call'd the Colledge of <hi>Lewis the Great.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Therefore, Sir, never tarry till Heaven shall Thunder-strike your Father. Summon an As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of the States General; call to your aid the Kings and States against whom he has wag'd such bloody Wars. Humble your self to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly See: I dare be answerable for your good Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess; nor can you wish for a more favourable Conjuncture. The People pant and thirst after Liberty; all <hi>France</hi> has her Eyes fix'd upon you; the Nobility, the Clergy, the Officers both Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and Civil, all will rise to raise you to the Throne. The Princes and States of <hi>Europe</hi> are
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:35027:75"/> weary of the War. His Holiness holds you forth his Arms, and looks upon you as a Son that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims the Rebellions of a Father, that has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd himself an Enemy to the Church: And it will be your fault, if there be not a general Peace.</p>
               <p>I would not, Sir, that the King should be dealt with, as <hi>Henry</hi> IV. his Son <hi>Henry,</hi> who bereav'd him of his Crown, reduc'd him to that extream Poverty, that sometimes he wanted Bread. And such was the bestial fury of that young Prince, that his Father dying at <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ige,</hi> and the Citizens having buried him in their Cathedral Church, his Son caus'd his Body to be taken up again, and carried to <hi>Spire,</hi> where it lay five years in the Chappel of St. <hi>Afren,</hi> as unworthy of Burial, because he died Excommunicated.</p>
               <p>A King is punished sufficiently by being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd; and it is Impiety for a Son, to insult o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Father's Misfortunes, tho' he drew them upon himself Therefore it will be your best way to make choice of some devout and pleasant Place, where he may live in plenty, and have that Respect paid him by all People, that may convince him it was not your desire to Reign, but your own and the safety of the Kingdom that importun'd you to depose him. I cannot set, Sir, before your eyes, a more Noble Example than that of the Prince and Princess of <hi>Orange.</hi> Let Men say what they please: <hi>James</hi> the II. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws, deserv'd to be Abdicated from the Throne. That same Prince, blinded by a false Zeal, had overturn'd all the Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>England.</hi> Contrary to the Priviledges of the Kingdom he would have set up a Religion, to the prejudice of that Establish'd by Law.</p>
               <p>He had almost reduc'd the Nation into Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:35027:76"/> What do the <hi>English</hi> in this Condition? They complain to the Presumptive Heirs of the Crown; and the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as being one of those, Lands with an Army in <hi>England:</hi> upon which the King betakes himself to flight.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was perswaded, that if a Parliament were call'd, and that the King his Father-in-Law were declar'd to have abdicated the Government, the Princess his Wife would be advanc'd to the Throne. There needed no more for him to do, when he saw he had the Hearts of all the <hi>English,</hi> but to have fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King's Army. Nevertheless the P. avoided fighting the K's Army, that he might not be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to fight against his Wife's Father. He sets forth in his Declaraion, that he came not to Dethrone him, but to restore the Laws of a Kingdom, of which the Princess his Wife was the Presumptive Heir: That he would call a Free Parliament, and leave the Nation to be the Judges of the King's Destiny. The King who knew himself guilty, betakes himself to an inglorious flight, after he had undone in four Days all that he had been four Years a doing, to attain a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spotick Power. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> never pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su'd, but when luckily for the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and unfortunately for <hi>James</hi> the II. he was lookt upon as gone, the King was stopp'd; but the Prince declares him still to be at liberty, and that it was for him to call a Parliament, and refer it to their Decision, according to the Laws of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>It is not very certain, Sir, whether a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would have been very favourable to <hi>James</hi> the II. or No. But by wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> several of the Bishops, and a good number of the Lords have since acted, we may guess that they had no intention
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:35027:76"/> to abdicate him. But however it were, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the manner wherein the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> proceeded; if <hi>James</hi> the II. had been abdicated in his favour, as he was afterwards by his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion, it is certain that he would have been so generous to that unfortunate Monarch, that it would have much lessen'd his Grief for being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of his Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>Follow then the Example of <hi>William</hi> the III. For whatsoever our <hi>French-men</hi> say, to ingratiate themselves with <hi>James</hi> II. and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. who is his Protector; the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is a Prince who merits no less Applause, for the Respect which he has shewed to <hi>James</hi> II. than for his Heroick Vertues.</p>
               <p>What would you have a Prince have done, when a whole Nation made their Complaint to him? Would you have had him suffer'd a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch to Reign, who had enslaved his People, who every day violated the Sacred Laws of the Kingdom, who extended his Arbitrary Power every day, and discountenanc'd the Grandees of his Court that oppos'd his Violences, and who like <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. suffer'd himself to be govern'd by a Jesuite.</p>
               <p>There was a necessity for him to do what he did; nor is there any Prince in the World, who would have done what he did, had he been in his place. But perhaps there would have been but few that would have behaved themselves with that respect to <hi>James</hi> the II. as he did; and who would not have made sure of Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms by doing more than he did.</p>
               <p>Pardon me, Great Sir, that I have said thus much, in speaking of your Father; 'tis the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern which I have for his Salvation, and your own Interest, and the love which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have for my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:35027:77"/> that have wrested these Truths from me.</p>
               <p>How happy Sir, will you be, and how happy will <hi>France</hi> be, would you but listen to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrances, if you understand how to benefit by them. However there would be something wanting to your own, and the happiness of your Subjects, should you stop there: There must be something more done, than only the pulling down of <hi>Lew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> the XIV. from his Throne. You must expel the Jesuits, who are the Cause of all the Misfortunes that have befallen your Kingdom: For to that Society alone it is, that we must impute all those Overturnings that have brought it so neer to Ruin. The Jesuits were the Men that put the King upon these unheard of Cruelties which he has exercised upon the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of St. <hi>Austin,</hi> and the Nuns of the <hi>Infancy.</hi> The <hi>Jesuits</hi> were they that instigated him against <hi>Innocent</hi> the XI. because they suspected him to be a Jesuite. They were the Men that forc'd him to use his faithful Subjects the Protestants after a manner so barbarous and unworthy of a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Prince. They were the Men, who to aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize themselves, forc'd him to declare a War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Emperour and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who are both Catholick Princes. In short, they are the Cause of all his Violences and Adulteries. For if his Confessor, who is a Jesuit, had ever refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to absolve him at his Confessions, would he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have continued in such a deadly sin for so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years together? But these Fathers find out ways to reconcile Heaven and Earth together. 'Tis a piece of their Religion to permit some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the greatest sins, <hi>for the greater Glory os God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the Interest of all Princes to exterminate the Jesuits, for they are the Murderers of Kings. Nor is it the Interest of any Kingdom, so much
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:35027:77"/> as of <hi>France,</hi> which to this day declares the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Death of <hi>Henry the Great.</hi> You can never be safe, so long as this Society has any footing in your Kingdom. A Parracide costs them nothing, and they will always find <hi>Ravilliack</hi>'s enough: for they always number them among the Martyrs that Assassinate Princes. But it will signifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, Sir, to expel the Jesuits out of your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if you continue a Persecutor like <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. It would be no Persecution to banish a Society which is a publick Nuisance; but it would be one of the most horrible things in the World not to give Toleration to the Protestants, who have nothing of Evil in their Morals, but have always stuck close to their Kings: you must therefore renew their Edicts, and heap your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours upon them in a larger measure than ever <hi>Henry</hi> the IV.</p>
               <p>If Christianity did not instruct you that a Prince ought never to persecute his Subjects for their Belief, you are bound to allow them Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration out of meer Policy. Cast your Eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Histories of past Ages, and you shall see the terrible Effects that a Restraint in Matters of Religion has produced: It has laid waste most flourishing and wealthy Provinces: It has rendred odious and execrable to Posterity, the Princes that have made use of it: It is the only Cause of Seditions and Insurrections, for the most part fatal to the Persecutors. What is <hi>Spain</hi> at this day, that great and flourishing Kingdom, which was heretofore so wealthy, and well stor'd with Inhabitants? What is it now but sad Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, dispeopled by the violance exercised upon Consciences, and the abominable Severities of the Inquisition Tribunal: and not to go farther in search of what you have before your Eyes,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:35027:78"/> what is <hi>France</hi> at this day, but a frightful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, only because they would constrain the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants to abandon their Religion, and turn <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the other side, behold the happiness of those States where Liberty of Conscience reigns. There all things are in a flouri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing Condition, Arts, Sciences, and Commerce. All People live there in Plenty You would think them so many swarms of People. Every one lives there at ease, and in so sweet a Tranquility, that there is nothing compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Felicity which those People enjoy, whose Magistrates and Princes abhor Persecution.</p>
               <p>I shall conclude, Sir, with what Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> concludes his Politick Will and Testament. You will be happy, you will be rich, you will be potent, if you can but win the Affection of the People.</p>
               <p>The ancient Kings your Predecessors, had such a particular value for the hearts of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that some of them thought it better to be King of the <hi>French,</hi> than King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed this Nation has been always e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem'd so passionately loyal to their Princes, that the People have been applauded by celebrated Authors, for being always ready to shed their Blood, and spend their Estates for the Service and Honour of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Under the Kings of the first and second Race, and of the third also till <hi>Philip the Fair,</hi> the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of Hearts was accompted the only publick Good and Safety of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Live happy then, Sir, and long may Heaven preserve you for the welfare and safety of <hi>France.</hi> All honest French-men long to live under your illustrious Government, and Solace themselves for the Miseries they sustained under the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35027:78"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>